<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ColSci publications &amp; preprints</title>
<link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
<atom:link href="https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.9.12</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Distinct NIR Reflectance Spectra Associated with Foliar Symptoms of Beech Leaf Disease</title>
  <dc:creator>Moore, E. G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dabydeen, L. C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Salha, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bichler, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Borsuk, A. M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Beech leaf disease (BLD) is an epidemic spreading among American beech (Fagus grandifolia) populations, with characteristic symptoms including dark green, yellow, or brown bands of thickened leaf tissue between secondary veins. Whereas near infrared (NIR) light is reflected by leaf tissue structure, here we used multispectral NIR imaging to distinguish symptomatic from asymptomatic leaf reflectance, as well as to distinguish between different expressions of symptoms (dark green, yellow, and brown bands) within symptomatic leaves. Key findings include significantly higher NIR reflectance in dark green bands of symptomatic tissue compared to asymptomatic tissue ({lambda} = 840, 860, 900, 940, and 980 nm; [~]26.2%, 25.9%, 35.0%, 35.3%, and 32.5% increase respectively). A partial least squares regression model predicted 97% of variation in symptomatic vs. asymptomatic NIR reflectance was attributed primarily to the increase in spongy mesophyll thickness and overall leaf thickness in symptomatic tissue. Water infiltration of the intercellular airspaces in symptomatic and asymptomatic leaves removed differences in NIR reflectance, supporting a mechanistic link between increased NIR reflectance and the foliar symptoms of BLD. Our results highlight the interaction of leaf internal architecture with NIR wavelengths, and informs the development of targeted remote sensing tools, with implications for detecting even early-stage symptoms of BLD.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Chemogenetic modulation of luciferase emission color for imaging and sensing</title>
  <dc:creator>Manirakiza, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shpinov, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gontier, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>El Hajji, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jullien, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gautier, A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Bioluminescent luciferases have emerged as powerful tools for bioimaging, enabling to image biological systems without external excitation light, reducing thus phototoxicity and eliminating background autofluorescence. Advanced imaging requires luciferases that deliver high photon output for enhanced sensitivity, tunable emission colors for multicolor imaging, and red-shifted emission for effective deep tissue imaging. Here, we introduce LumiFAST, a small tunable luciferase engineered by fusing the bright blue-light emitting NanoLuc with the tunable chemogenetic fluorescent reporter pFAST. pFAST binds and stabilizes the fluorescent state of a variety of synthetic fluorogenic chromophores (also called fluorogens). Its proximity with NanoLuc leads to efficient bioluminescence resonance energy transfer (BRET), enabling customizable red-shifted emission. Thanks to the small size of pFAST, LumiFAST maintains a compact structure, while its modular design allows emission color to be tuned from cyan to green, yellow, orange and red simply by changing the fluorogen. Systematic optimization of the fusion topology and linker length yielded an optimal variant with apparent BRET efficiencies reaching up to 90 %. The red-shifted emission of LumiFAST enables dual-color microscopy imaging when used alongside NanoLuc and allows imaging through thick scattering media. Beyond imaging, our insights into the structural factors governing efficient BRET allowed us to engineer biosensors based on NanoLuc and pFAST for the visualization of protease activity and protein-protein interactions in live cells.</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Peculiar Pigment Pattern and Population Profile of a Poisonous Pufferfish</title>
  <dc:creator>Miyazawa, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Doi, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Takahashi, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nishiyama, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shigenobu, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Misawa, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kikuchi, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sakai, H.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Pufferfish are well-known for their toxicity, yet they also exhibit a remarkable diversity of pigment patterns. Mushifugu (Takifugu exascurus) is a pufferfish endemic to Japan&#39;s coastal waters and is characterized by conspicuous labyrinthine patterns. Despite being recorded along both the Sea of Japan and the Pacific coasts, it has a limited distribution and is infrequently observed. Aside from its unique body pattern, mushifugu shows little to no morphological differences from other Takifugu species, often leading to speculation that it may be an interspecific hybrid. In addition, previous theoretical and empirical studies have shown that complex camouflage-like labyrinthine patterns can emerge through the &#39;pattern blending&#39; caused by hybridization between spotted species, providing support for this possibility. Here, we investigate the phylogenetic origin of mushifugu and its distinctive pattern through population structure analysis and demographic inference in comparison with its closest spotted relative, komonfugu (T. flavipterus). Mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) analysis revealed two regional haplogroups within mushifugu--one in the Sea of Japan (SJ) and the other in the Pacific Ocean (PO). In the haplotype network, the SJ haplogroup formed a distinct cluster, whereas the PO haplogroup appeared as its own cluster connected to the komonfugu haplogroup. By contrast, genome-wide SNP analyses indicated limited structure between the SJ and PO mushifugu populations, while clearly separating mushifugu from komonfugu. Coalescent-based demographic inference suggested that the two species diverged following a bottleneck event in the early Pleistocene. These results confirm that mushifugu is a distinct species rather than a recent interspecific hybrid. Nevertheless, evidence of introgression was detected in both mitochondrial and nuclear genomes, suggesting multiple episodes of past hybridization between mushifugu and komonfugu, highlighting the potentially complex evolutionary processes shaping Takifugu species and their pigment patterns.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>MicroRNA166-HD-ZIP III module impacts tuber shape, color and productivity in potato</title>
  <dc:creator>Patil, N. S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Vasav, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kumari, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Arora, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Natarajan, B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Banerjee, A. K.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>MicroRNA165/166 is a highly conserved and abundant microRNA family in plants that targets class III homeodomain leucine zipper (HD-ZIP III) transcription factors. Their essential roles in plant development, organ polarity, meristem maintenance, and vascular differentiation have been well established. However, their role in storage organ development, particularly in potato tuberization remains unknown. Here, we demonstrate the pleiotropic effects of miR166 on potato (Solanum tuberosum spp. Andigena) growth and development. Suppression of miR166 via target mimicry (MIM166) resulted in reduced plant height, altered vascular patterning, diminished leaf curvature, and impaired root development. Remarkably, MIM166 lines produced elongated, pigmented tubers with reduced yield under short-day conditions. Transcriptomic analyses of swollen head versus stalk of tuberizing stolons revealed altered expression of auxin-, cytokinin-, and gibberellin-related genes, consistent with hormone quantification data, suggesting the key role of phytohormones in governing tuber shape. Anthocyanin profiling indicated elevated accumulation of cyanidin 3-glucoside, pelargonidin 3-glucoside, and delphinidin 3-glucoside in MIM166 tuber peels, correlating with the upregulation of anthocyanin biosynthetic genes. Tuber productivity in these lines was reduced possibly due to the decreased expression of SWEET11b and distorted vascular structures in the MIM166 lines. Further, StREVOLUTA, a direct miR166 target, exhibited dynamic expression during stolon differentiation and could modulate the expression of auxin biosynthesis genes. Collectively, our results demonstrate that the miR166-HD-ZIP III module is functional in potato, plays conserved roles in regulating key developmental traits, and is active through early stolon-to-tuber transition stages, affecting tuber shape, color and productivity.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Predictive Networks Generate Motion-Induced Color Illusions</title>
  <dc:creator>Ueda, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sinapayen, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Watanabe, E.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Subjective color (SC) refers to chromatic perception induced by achromatic stimuli, as classically demonstrated using Benham\&#39;s top. Despite nearly two centuries of investigation, the underlying neural mechanisms remain unclear. We developed artificial neural network (ANN) models trained on natural videos using predictive learning to investigate SC generation. These models successfully reproduced artificial subjective color (ASC) despite the absence of explicit color information in the training stimuli. Critically, ASC characteristics were systematically influenced by the colors of moving objects in the training videos. Using progressively simplified stimuli, ranging from natural scenes to 3D computer graphics to 2D animations, we demonstrated that the colors of moving objects are the primary determinant of ASC properties. We propose that predictive learning establishes color associations with motion patterns, causing the arcs on Benham\&#39;s top to be perceived as moving objects with their corresponding colors. These findings suggest that cortical predictive mechanisms may complement retinal processes in generating subjective color phenomena.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Insertion of an invading retrovirus regulates a novel color trait in swordtail fish</title>
  <dc:creator>Haghani, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dodge, T. O.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baczenas, J. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gunn, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>He, Q.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pangburn, W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sood, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Du, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fascinetto-Zago, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kaatmann, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ou, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dougan, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Olmos-Santiago, N. S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Preising, G. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Payne, C. Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Haase Cox, S. K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hunnicutt, K. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Madrzyk, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Moran, B. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Stigloher, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Powell, D. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Schartl, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gifford, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Han, G. z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Schumer, M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>For over a century, evolutionary biologists have been motivated to understand the mechanisms through which organisms adapt to their environments. Coloration and pigmentation are remarkably variable within and between species and can serve as an important window into the mechanisms of adaptation. Here, we map the genetic basis of a newly described iridescence trait in swordtail fish to a single locus. Individuals with this trait appear to sparkle as they move through the water. We find that the trait is driven by the recent endogenization of a retrovirus that inserted near the gene alkal2a. This insertion is associated with changes in the chromatin landscape, upregulation of alkal2a, and accumulation of iridescent cells that adhere to the scales. Rather than causing diseases, our results demonstrate that invading endogenous retroviruses can also regulate novel trait variation in the host. Moreover, we find that this coloration trait may act as an important signal in interactions between fish and their predators in the natural environment.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Anthropogenic factors explain wing colour variation in Colias (Lepidoptera: Pieridae) across the Toronto urbanization gradient</title>
  <dc:creator>Sabatino, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jahner, J. P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>McFarlane, S. E.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Hybridization, or interbreeding between two previously diverged populations, is increasing due to human influences on the environment. Rates of hybridization might be increasing particularly quickly among urban species, especially those that are known to be sensitive to environmental disturbances. Butterflies are one such taxa, as some species are commonly found in urban areas, despite being sensitive indicators. For example, Colias philodice and C. eurytheme (Lepidoptera: Pieridae) hybridize when their ranges are in contact or overlap and are commonly found in large cities throughout North America. However, it is an open question how variation in urbanization might affect variation in hybridization. Using wild Colias across a gradient of urbanization in Toronto, Ontario, we tested how the variation in Colias colour, as an indicator of hybridization, relates to human disturbance and urbanization. We created an objective numeric classification for both C. eurytheme and C. philodice, against which we categorized Colias samples. We found that some of the urbanization metrics, including distance to road, Julian date, and number of pedestrians affect the variation in Colias colour, suggesting that urbanization affects Colias colouration, and potentially rates of hybridization, in Toronto. This means that human disturbance of the environment could be affecting Colias rates of hybridization.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Estimating resource acquisition and water-use traits in wine grapes using reflectance spectroscopy</title>
  <dc:creator>Mariani, R. O.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Isaac, M. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cathline, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Robertson, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Martin, A. R.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>In agroecosystems, the variable expression of crop functional traits is expected to play a role in key processes, including plant nutrient cycling and water acquisition, that confer ecosystem resistance and/ or resilience to environmental change. The ability to estimate crop trait data is therefore critical to predict crop responses to environmental change, enabling more informed diagnosis of crop performance and on-farm management strategies. Yet, many traditional methods for quantifying plant traits are time-consuming and resource-intensive, limiting sample sizes and study durations. In response, high-throughput phenotyping--specifically reflectance spectroscopy-- has emerged as a key element of plant trait research, capable of estimating plant traits more rapidly. However, little is known about whether or not reflectance spectroscopy can detect within-species variation in resource acquisition and plant-water traits. Using wine grapes (V. vinifera subsp. vinifera) as a focal crop, this study aimed to assess the ability of reflectance spectroscopy and the subsequent partial least squares regression modelling approach to quantify intraspecific variation in 12 functional traits across 12 different cultivars. Results showed significant differences in traits, especially in the photosynthetic and hydraulic traits, among closely related cultivars, falling along a resource-conservative to resource-acquisitive axis of variation. We also found that reflectance differentiated this fine-scale trait variation, specifically in leaf chemical and morphological traits, contributing to higher accuracy, and indicating that this HTP approach is viable for detailed trait estimation in diverse agroecosystems.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A 37-color spectral flow cytometry panel to characterize phenotype and cytokine expression in human intestinal T cells</title>
  <dc:creator>Lindelauf, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jiang, Q.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Koning, F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>van der Meulen-de Jong, A. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>van Unen, V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pascutti, M. F.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>We developed a 37-color spectral flow cytometry panel to characterize T cell function, with a focus CD4+ T helper (Th) cells, in the human intestine. The panel includes lineage-defining transcription factors, markers for memory status, tissue residency and T cell activation, and 11 cytokines representing multiple Th cell lineages. The panel is currently being used to investigate CD4+ Th cell function in intestinal and peripheral blood samples of inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) patients. The panel could however be applied to investigate both peripheral and tissue-resident T cell function in a range of immune-mediated diseases.</description>
  <category>immunology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sensory receptor expansion and neural accommodation in butterfly color vision</title>
  <dc:creator>Gao, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ainsworth, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Donati, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zhao, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ragsac, M. F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Genduso, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Andre, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tomlinson, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Perry, M. W.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The evolution of more complex brains required existing neurons and neural circuits to accommodate new inputs. The genetic and developmental mechanisms that enable such integration are largely unknown. Butterflies evolved more complex retinal mosaics through the addition of a second R7 color photoreceptor per ommatidium (unit eye). In Drosophila, the unique R7 makes a stochastic choice to express one of two opsin genes. In butterflies, the two R7s make two independent stochastic cell fate choices in each ommatidium, producing three ommatidial types instead of the two in flies. Here, we investigate the developmental basis of this change and how the butterfly brain accommodates an expansion in sensory receptor input. We first identified the developmental mechanisms that specify the second R7 cell. We then modified Drosophila retinas to have butterfly-like transcription factor expression, causing recruitment of an additional R7. The two R7s make independent stochastic choices, like butterflies, leading to three stochastically distributed ommatidial types instead of two. In Drosophila, each of the two subtypes of R7s connects to one of two types of Dm8 neurons. Dm8 neurons of both types are born in excess, with Dm8s that are not connected to their cognate R7s undergoing apoptosis. In the presence of extra R7s in butterfly-like retinas, additional Dm8s are retained, leading to two Dm8s per medulla column. We propose a model in which population-level variation in the ratio of R7 subtypes produced in the retina maintains an excess pool of two types of potentially interacting partners in the brain, thus providing developmental flexibility which allows brains to accommodate additional inputs. We demonstrate how excess neurons that are eliminated in normal development facilitated the expansion of color vision in butterflies, and similar cooption events may represent a general mechanism of neural evolution.</description>
  <category>developmental biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Opposing seasonal dynamics in phylogenetic and flower color diversity of co-flowering wildflower assemblages</title>
  <dc:creator>Talbot, C. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Weber, M. G.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Flower color is a key trait mediating plant-pollinator interactions, yet the ecological rules governing its distribution across co-flowering assemblages remain poorly understood. We examined spatiotemporal patterns of flower color and phylogenetic diversity in Eastern North American wildflowers to test for non-random community structure, seasonal shifts, and associations between flower color similarity and phylogenetic relatedness. Using occurrence, phenology, and color data from community science datasets, we reconstructed communities of co-flowering assemblages and calculated standardized effect sizes of mean pairwise distances for both flower color and phylogenetic relatedness. We analyzed seasonal trends using mixed models and assessed whether closely related species co-flowered non-randomly with respect to color similarity using bootstrap correlations. We found that, on average, co-flowering assemblages were overdispersed for both flower color and phylogeny. However, flower color dispersion significantly decreased over the growing season, while phylogenetic dispersion significantly increased, reflecting a pattern in which co-flowering assemblages shifted to more distantly related but similarly colored assemblages. Finally, color and phylogenetic dispersion were negatively correlated across communities, indicating that communities composed of more closely related species tended to exhibit more dissimilar flowers. Together, our results suggest that wildflower assemblages in Eastern North America show detectable, non-random structure across space and time with respect to color and relatedness at the broad scale, and that mechanisms underlying the structure of co-flowering groups may shift throughout the growing season.</description>
  <category>ecology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Genomic and genetic insights into speciation and pigment pattern diversification in Danio fishes</title>
  <dc:creator>Lu, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Podobnik, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Huang, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>McCluskey, B. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>McCarthy, S. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wood, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Collins, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Torrance, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sims, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gao, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Huang, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liu, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fang, W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Huang, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ma, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Parichy, D. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Irion, U.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liu, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Howe, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Postlethwait, J. H.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The Danioninae subfamily of teleost fishes boasts up to four hundred distinct species that have evolved to display a stunning diversity of morphological forms. Here we use newly assembled genome sequences of four laboratory and wild zebrafish strains as well as eleven species of the Danio and Danionella genera to explore their phylogenetic history and the genetic basis of pigment pattern diversification. Phylogenomic analyses uncover extensive introgression and incomplete lineage sorting that have obscured phylogenetic relationships within Danio and corroborate an ancient hybrid origin of zebrafish. Whereas D. rerio inherited ancestral horizontal stripes, relatives repeatedly evolved spots and vertical bars. Interspecific complementation tests reveal functional divergence of the adhesion molecule gene igsf11 and the gap junction gene gja5b between the striped zebrafish and Danio species with divergent patterns. Comparative genomic and transcriptomic analyses suggest that protein and regulatory evolution have accompanied pigment pattern diversification. Our analyses elucidate complex genetic changes underlying the phylogenetic history and morphological diversification in the Danio genus. Resolved phylogenetic relationships, available genome assemblies, transcriptomes, and genetic tractability establish Danio fish species as excellent models for biomedical research in vertebrates.</description>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Perceiving surface colour requires attention</title>
  <dc:creator>Goddard, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Paul Remician, K.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Colour constancy refers to our ability to distinguish changes in surface properties from changes in the properties of light illuminating the scene. The apparent ease with which we can tell that objects do not change colour, for example, when moving from sunlight to the shade, belies the complexity of solving this ill-constrained problem. Although there is a substantial body of work testing which image cues might be used to accomplish this, there is surprisingly little known of how the brain performs this computation. Here, we tested a fundamental aspect of this perceptual process: whether it requires attention. We measured visual search times for both surface colour (requiring separation of surface and illuminant properties) and &#39;raw&#39;, colorimetric colour (which does not). We found a clear difference between the two: visual search for colorimetric colour was fast and near-parallel, while search for surface colour was slow and consistent with the serial deployment of attention. That is, search times suggest that the perceptual separation of surface and illuminant properties in colour constancy may require an attention-based process analogous to perceiving conjunctions of simple features in &#39;feature binding&#39;. Colour discrimination thresholds suggested that while colorimetric colour detection is fast and parallel, once attention was directed to these stimuli and perceptual scission occurs, colorimetric colour information was discarded by the visual system. These results offer important new insights into the sequence of processes the brain uses to accomplish colour constancy.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Color, size, shape: The drivers of floral variation in Hesperis matronalis (Dames Rocket)</title>
  <dc:creator>Johnson, S. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Rifkin, J. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wright, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baucom, R. S.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Evolutionary biologists have long been intrigued by the factors that sustain genetic and phenotypic variation within and among natural populations. Polymorphisms underlying components of floral display -- such as floral color, size, and shape -- are uniquely of interest since variation in these traits impact pollinator attraction, rates of visitation, and pollinator efficiency, which ultimately influence patterns of plant reproduction and therefore fitness. We leverage existing floral variation present within and among populations of Hesperis matronalis (Dames Rocket) to disentangle the relative influence of natural selection and genetic drift in shaping floral trait variation. We employ a multi-tiered approach: we determine if variation in floral traits (color, size, and petal shape) is influenced by geography or environmental variables such as temperature and precipitation, we evaluate whether selection underlies trait variation by comparing phenotypic divergence (PST) with neutral genetic structure (FST), and we perform a Lande-Arnold selection analysis to explore the relationship between fitness and floral trait variation within natural populations. We find that selection underlies the divergence of floral color, floral size, and petal width among H. matronalis populations, with PST &gt; FST for each trait. We find no indication, however, that variation in size in this species is influenced by the environment, but some evidence that variation in floral color and petal shape may be influenced by temperature. Finally, selection analyses of contemporary populations indicate divergent selection affecting combinations of color, petal shape, and plant size. These results suggest that the variation in floral shape in this species may be maintained due to environmental pressures, whereas floral color is influenced by pollinator visibility and the presence of different pollinator groups.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Effects of color-enhancing filters on color salience in normal trichromats</title>
  <dc:creator>Webster, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Knoblauch, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Simoncelli, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>McPherson, D.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Notch filters can alter color contrasts by selectively filtering different spectral bands of the stimulus and have been developed to enhance reddish-greenish contrasts for color-deficient observers with anomalous trichromacy. We examined the effects of such filters on color salience for normal trichromats, using a visual search paradigm where the task was to locate a color target superimposed on a variegated chromatic background, similar to foraging for fruits among foliage. Background colors varied along a bluish-yellowish or purplish to yellow-green (short-wave cone isolating) axis, roughly spanning the range of dominant color variations in arid or lush environments. Target colors sampled a wide range of hue angles and contrasts. Testing was conducted on a computer monitor, with the filter effects simulated by calculating corresponding chromaticities with or without the filter for naturalistic (Munsell) reflectances. The filter evaluated (Enchroma SuperX glasses) was designed to increase color contrast along a magenta-green axis. Consistent with this, search times for targets on the blue-yellow background were significantly faster for the filter condition, because the filter increased the target-background color difference. Alternatively, overall differences in search times were not observed for the S-cone background. The differences on the two backgrounds could be qualitatively accounted for by the relative salience of the stimuli predicted by a perceptual color space (CIELAB). Our results demonstrate the efficacy of the filters for enhancing visual performance for normal trichromats and naturalistic tasks, and illustrate how these effects depend on the potential color characteristics of the environment.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The hallmark of colour in EEG signal</title>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Our perception of the world is inherently colourful, and colour provides well-documented benefits for vision: it helps us see things quicker and remember them better. We hypothesised that colour is not only central to perception but also a rich and decodable source of information in electroencephalography (EEG) signal recorded non-invasively from the scalp. Previous work has shown that brain activity carries colour information for uniform patches, but it remains unclear whether this extends to natural, complex images where colour is not explicitly cued. To investigate this, we analysed the THINGS EEG dataset, comprising 64-channel recordings from participants viewing 1,800 distinct objects (16,740 images) for 100 ms each, totalling over 82,000 trials. We established a perceptual colour ground truth through a psychophysical experiment in which participants viewed each image for 100 ms and selected perceived colours from a 13-option palette. An artificial neural network trained to predict these scene-level colour distributions directly from EEG signals showed that colour information was robustly decodable (average F-score of 0.5). We next modelled the interaction between colour and object perception in neuroimaging decoding. Images were segmented using the Segment Anything Model (SAM), each object was assigned a representative colour, and features were extracted from these colour-augmented images using CLIP vision encoders. We trained an EEG encoder, CUBE (ColoUr and oBjEct decoding), to align features in both object and colour spaces. Across EEG and MEG datasets in a 200-class recognition task, incorporating colour improved decoding accuracy by about 5%. Together, these findings demonstrate that EEG signal recorded during natural vision carries substantial colour information that interacts with object perception. Modelling this mutual interaction enhances neural decoding performance.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Modeling MEK-inhibitor Associated Retinopathy in vitro using human induced-1 pluripotent stem cell-derived retinal pigment epithelial cells</title>
  <dc:creator>Lozano, L. P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jennisch, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jensen, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ratcliff, J. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wiley, L. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Harman, B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Riker, M. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wright, A. T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Erickson, B. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Boldt, H. C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Boyce, T. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mullins, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Binkley, E. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tucker, B. A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Pharmacologic inhibitors of MEK are important anti-cancer drugs but can result in MEK-inhibitor Associated Retinopathy (MEKAR) in which vision is lost due to serous retinal detachments that form via an unknown mechanism. We hypothesized that the cause of this side effect is drug-induced dysfunction of retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) cells. To test this hypothesis, we used human induced pluripotent stem cell-derived RPE cells. We treated mature, hiPSC-derived RPE cells with selumetinib and measured impacts on RPE-specific function, structure, and gene expression. Selumetinib increases the ability of hiPSC-derived RPE to internalize bovine rod outer segments (1.9 vs 3.0, p=0.0024). It also decreases expression of aquaporin 1 during the first 10 days of treatment (2.7 vs 1.1, p=0.0015). It has no effect on the ability of hiPSC-derived RPE to maintain membrane integrity. Selumetinib alters gene expression of hiPSC-derived RPE, with significant changes in genes involved in transport of ions and small molecules regulating cell volume and lysosomal acidification. Selumetinib may lead to subretinal fluid accumulation by both increasing secretions into this space and decreasing outflow.</description>
  <category>molecular biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Aposematic color patterns are the dominant axis of phenotypic diversification in Nymphalid butterflies</title>
  <dc:creator>Luerig, M. D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shirai, L. T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mota, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Willmott, K. R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Freitas, A. V. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Porto, A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Butterfly wing patterns serve diverse roles in visual communication, from aposematic signaling and mimicry to mate attraction and camouflage. In brush-footed butterflies (Nymphalidae), this diversity can be traced to the wing pattern &quot;ground plan&quot; that generates phenotypes deterministic in origin yet highly multidimensional in form. Quantifying such complexity at scale has long been a challenge, limiting our understanding of how visual signals interact, constrain one another, and evolve. Here, we used computer vision to extract high-dimensional traits from standardized museum specimens and assembled the largest comparative dataset of wing color patterns to date, spanning over one third of all known Nymphalid species. We first tested whether chemically defended species occupy a distinct region in morphospace and then derived a quantitative score for aposematism from the principal color patterns associated with defense. Using this score, we examined whether aposematic signals are expressed consistently across wing surfaces and sexes, and whether their origins are linked to shifts in evolutionary rate. We found that the dominant axis of morphospace is defined by chromatic and achromatic contrast, along which defended and undefended species cluster. Validation with an expert-labeled moth dataset confirmed that this axis separates aposematic from non-aposematic phenotypes across Lepidoptera. Consistent with theory, strongly aposematic species showed greater visual similarity between dorsal and ventral surfaces, between sexes, and among individuals. Rate analyses further indicated that aposematic patterns evolved repeatedly and were associated with non-linear shifts in evolutionary tempo. Together, these results identify aposematism as the dominant organizing axis of wing color pattern evolution in Nymphalidae.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A recurrent sequencing artifact on Illumina sequencers with two-color fluorescent dye chemistry and its impact on somatic variant detection</title>
  <dc:creator>Fu, B. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Viswanadham, V. V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Maziec, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jin, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Park, P. J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The sequencing-by-synthesis technology by Illumina, Inc. enables efficient and scalable readouts of mutations from genomic data. To enhance sequencing speed and efficiency, Illumina has shifted from the four-color base calling chemistry of the HiSeq series to a two-color fluorescent dye chemistry in the NovaSeq series. Benchmarking sequencing artifacts due to biases in the newer chemistry is important to evaluate the quality of identified mutations. We re-analyzed a series of whole-genome sequencing experiments in which the same samples were sequenced on the NovaSeq 6000 (two-color) and HiSeq X10 (four-color) platforms by independent groups. In several samples, we observed a higher frequency of T-to-G and A-to-C substitutions (&quot;T&gt;G&quot;) at the read level for NovaSeq 6000 versus HiSeq X10. As the per-base error rate is still low, the artifactual substitutions have a negligible effect in identifying germline or high variant allele frequency (VAF) somatic mutations. However, such errors can confound the detection of low-VAF somatic variants in high-depth sequencing samples, particularly in studies of mosaic mutations in normal tissues, where variants have low read support and are called without a matched normal. The artifactual T&gt;G variant calls disproportionately occur at NT[TG] trinucleotides, and we leveraged this observation to bioinformatically reduce the T&gt;G excess in somatic mutation callsets. We identified a recurrent artifact specific to the Illumina two-color chemistry platform on the NovaSeq 6000 with the potential to contaminate low-VAF somatic mutation calls. Thus, an unexpected enrichment of T&gt;G mutations in mosaicism studies warrants caution.</description>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Structural basis for color tuning and passive ion conductance in red-shifted pump-fold channelrhodopsin ChR024</title>
  <dc:creator>Takeno, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tajima, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kim, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tsujimura, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ito, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sugiura, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yamashita, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kishi, K. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fukuda, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nakamura, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Watanabe, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ikeda, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Katayama, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Furutani, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kandori, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ishikita, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Inoue, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kato, H. E.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>ChR024 is a cation-conducting channelrhodopsin with a red-shifted absorption spectrum, recently discovered from a previously unidentified clade through machine-learning-guided gene mining. Due to its unique position in the phylogenetic tree and distinctive spectral properties, it serves as an important model for elucidating rhodopsin evolution and for engineering optogenetic tools with enhanced performance, but its structure and function remain poorly understood. Here, we present cryo-electron microscopy structures of ChR024 in detergent micelles and lipid nanodiscs at resolutions of 3.2 and 2.5 [A], respectively. The structures reveal an architecture strikingly similar to that of ion-pumping rhodopsins, even more so than other pump-like channelrhodopsins such as ChRmine. Structural, theoretical, and spectroscopic analyses uncover a unique color-tuning mechanism, in which charged residues close and distant from the retinal chromophore cooperatively modulate the pKa of the Schiff base counterion and thereby determine the absorption maximum wavelength. Finally, comparative structural analysis of channel- and pump-type rhodopsins, combined with electrophysiology, provides insights into the molecular boundary between these two functional classes and demonstrates the conversion of an outward proton pump into a light-gated channel. Together, these findings illuminate diverse mechanisms of color tuning and functional specification within the rhodopsin family, paving the way for the rational engineering of next-generation optogenetic tools.</description>
  <category>biophysics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
