<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ColSci publications &amp; preprints</title>
<link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
<atom:link href="https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.9.16</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>The cuticle lamellae responsible for structural coloration in red algae display common features with the metazoan extracellular matrix</title>
  <dc:creator>Philippe, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Godfroy, O.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Beisson, F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gautier, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jouanneau, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Le Panse, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Com, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Delage, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Czjzek, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ficko-Blean, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Collen, J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Structural coloration is a physical phenomenon observed in many living organisms, including seaweeds, via the formation of highly organized nanostructures. Although a widespread system is characterized by the deposition of multilayer thin-film in the extracellular matrix (ECM), enabling light interference, to date such lamellae have only been described in the cuticle of red algae belonging to the Gigartinaceae family within macroalgae. Here, we determine the composition of the multilayered cuticle components in the model species Chondrus crispus (Rhodophyta), using genomic, transcriptomic, proteomic, metabolomic and analytical profiling of carbohydrates. The complex structural assembly revealed common features with the ECM of animals. The carbohydrate fraction consists of a complex mixture of ECM carrageenans and glycosaminoglycan-like structures. A major von Willerbrand factor A domain (VWA) protein plays a critical role for the adhesion of macromolecules, including protein-protein interactions and to sulfated polysaccharides. We propose the name of Lamellae Cohesive Protein (LCP) regarding the alternate distribution of chemically distinct constituents within the cuticle. For the first time, we identified major proteins of the algal cuticle, providing a framework for addressing the evolutionary origins of the algal cuticle biosynthesis and raise important questions regarding its role, particularly across the life cycle marked by major structural ECM modifications.</description>
  <category>biochemistry</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lysosome-Related Organelles Orchestrate Guanine Crystal Formation in Pigment Cells</title>
  <dc:creator>Gorelick-Ashkenazi, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Barzilay, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lerer-Goldshtein, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Olender, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Eyal, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Glaser, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Broder, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mishol, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Deis, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kedmi, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gur, D.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Iridosomes, the guanine crystal-forming organelles of pigment-producing iridophores, are among the most versatile, visually striking yet mechanistically uncharacterized organelles in vertebrate biology. Lysosome-related organelles (LROs) support cell type-specific functions by adapting endolysosomal pathways for specialized roles. Here, we show that iridosomes represent a previously unrecognized subtype of LROs. Using transcriptomic profiling of zebrafish iridophores, CRISPR-Cas9-mediated gene disruption, and cryogenic transmission electron microscopy, we define the molecular program underlying iridosome biogenesis. Iridosomes have evolved unique adaptations for crystal growth while retaining core features of other LROs. Key regulators, including RAB32a, AP3M2, and HPS5, are essential for crystal formation, with gene knockouts causing reduced crystal number, altered morphology, and distinct maturation defects. We further identify hallmark LRO features in iridosomes, including intraluminal vesicles and pH-regulated developmental transitions. Cross-species transcriptomic analysis confirms that iridosomes share an LRO signature across vertebrates, including teleost fish and reptiles, suggesting ancient evolutionary origins. These findings establish iridosomes as crystalline LROs and as a model for investigating how cells construct structurally specialized organelles through coordinated trafficking, acid-base regulation, and crystallization, with implications for LRO evolution and human disease.</description>
  <category>developmental biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Environmental Variation Promotes Convergent Evolution and Rapid Diversification of Wing Shape and Color in Skipper Butterflies</title>
  <dc:creator>Matos-Maravi, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Linke, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ribeiro, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lamas, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Freitas, A. V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nunez, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kawahara, A. Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Toussaint, E. F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bacon, C. D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wahlberg, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Antonelli, A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Predation is a key driver of speciation and phenotypic diversification, yet how antipredator traits evolve and persist over evolutionary time remains poorly understood. We generated target sequence capture and whole-genome sequencing data for the skipper butterfly subfamily Eudaminae (Hesperiidae) to test whether antipredator defenses, in interaction with environmental variation, promote diversification. We focus on two antipredation wing traits: hindwing tails, which deflect predator attacks, and blue-green coloration, which may enhance motion dazzle and be used as warning coloration. Applying phylogenomics, morphometrics, and comparative methods, we model trait evolution in relation to diel activity and geographic distribution and find that hindwing tails repeatedly evolved at least seven times and blue-green coloration at least fifteen times. Both traits are associated with elevated speciation rates, but evolutionary transitions toward tailless wings and non-iridescent coloration occurred more frequently than trait gains, indicating high evolutionary lability of these antipredator defenses. Trait loss, particularly pronounced in tropical diurnal species, may reflect trade-offs in flight performance, shifts in predation guilds, or the evolution of alternative defensive traits. Our findings highlight rampant convergent evolution of wing traits that are under strong predator-mediated selection. By identifying how antipredator defenses and environmental contexts influence phenotypic and species diversification, this study provides new insights into the ecological and evolutionary processes underlying insect diversity.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Two-colour Imaging Fluorescence Correlation Spectroscopy (ImFCS) probes the influence of the juxta-membrane actin-cortex</title>
  <dc:creator>Talluri, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Krishna, P. S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wohland, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mayor, S.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Here we extend Imaging Fluorescence Correlation Spectroscopy (ImFCS), together with bright, photostable fluorophores, to quantify how the juxta-membranous actin cortex influences plasma membrane dynamics. This problem is technically challenging because the membrane is only a few nanometres thick, whereas the axial resolution of live-cell fluorescence imaging is on the order of 100 nm. We address this by engineering a membrane-anchored actin reporter that combines a weakly interacting actin-binding domain with bright, photostable fluorophores optimized for two-colour ImFCS. This design enables the generation of simultaneous, co-registered diffusion maps where the mobility of the reporter serves as a dynamic sensor for the local density of the cortical actin network. The actin-binding reporter displays diffusion coefficients spanning more than two orders of magnitude, in stark contrast to an otherwise similar reporter that cannot bind actin, which diffuses much faster and within a much narrower range. Thus, the mobility of the reporter becomes a sensitive spatial readout of actin-mediated constraints. By comparing, on a pixel-by-pixel basis, the diffusion of the actin-binding reporter with that of the non-binding mutant, we construct an actin-occupancy map that quantifies the fraction of the membrane functionally influenced by cortical actin. Using this approach, we find that the juxta-membrane actin cortex modulates transport over more than 80% of the cell surface. Our two-channel ImFCS strategy establishes diffusion-based comparison as a general methodology to map the functional footprint of the cortical cytoskeleton on live cell membranes.</description>
  <category>biophysics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Museum genomics links MC1R alleles to adaptive winter coat color polymorphism in the long-tailed weasel</title>
  <dc:creator>Pimenta, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Miranda, I.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Farelo, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Alvarenga, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mills, L. S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Melo-Ferreira, J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Understanding the architecture of biological adaptations is a major endeavor of evolutionary biology. Using Natural History collections, we study the genetic basis and evolution of white/brown winter coat color variation in the long-tailed weasel (Neogale frenata), a crucial phenological adaptation for camouflage in habitats with seasonal snow. We produced whole-genome sequencing data for museum specimens, along two winter color morph transition areas in North America, at the West and East coasts. Genome-wide association scans identified a single genomic region linked to color variation polymorphism with approximately 300kb and 200kb in the West and East regions, respectively, which included the pigmentation gene MC1R. We identified three MC1R alleles, two of which with deletions of nine or eight amino acids, alternatively associated with the winter brown morphs in the West and East, respectively. These deletions affect the second transmembrane domain, and in one case also the first extracellular loop, which in silico analyses predicted to impact the protein&#39;s function. Our findings show alternative intraspecific evolutionary solutions for environmental adaptation in long-tailed weasels, building on the evidence that major genes of the melanin production pathway are hotspots for recurrent and independent evolution of winter camouflage adaptation.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Temperature and Ultraviolet Radiation Drive Divergent Visible and Near-Infrared Reflectance Patterns in Butterflies</title>
  <dc:creator>Kou, C. Z. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kang, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Brindle, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Maclean, I.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bridle, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pigot, A. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wilson, R. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Williamson, J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>1. Climate change poses extreme risks to biodiversity, threatening the ecosystems upon which humanity depends. Understanding the traits that mediate how organisms respond to climatic gradients in space and time will enable better predictions of the taxa and ecological communities most at risk from warming. 2. In insects, colouration influences thermoregulation, but warming responses must be traded off against other selective pressures. We hypothesise that butterfly wing reflectance in visible and near-infrared (NIR) spectra respond differently to temperature and ultraviolet radiation over space and time. We combined existing reflectance data of 97 butterfly species in both NIR and visible wavelengths, with long-term abundance monitoring data of 120 butterfly communities sampled across 1650 m altitude gradients from May to August in two time periods (2004/5 and 2017). 3. The visible and NIR reflectances of butterfly communities showed a non-linear relationship with altitude, with the lowest reflectance (darkest butterflies) at the coolest, highest sites. In contrast, community visible reflectance decreased through the year as temperatures warmed over spring-summer, whereas community NIR reflectance remained constant, revealing divergent responses of reflectance types to seasonal changes. Temperature had opposing effects on visible and NIR reflectance of butterfly communities, where increasing temperature reduced community visible reflectance strongly while increasing community NIR reflectance slightly. 4. Considering the effects on reflectance of shared evolutionary history in a Bayesian hierarchical model for individual species, lighter-coloured (more reflective) species were associated with warmer temperatures - flying later in spring-summer or at lower altitudes. However, instead of decreasing in reflectance through the year and across temperature gradients, species instead became lighter, we expect as a result of a Simpson&#39;s paradox. 5. These results emphasise how visible and NIR reflectance wavelength bands mediate butterflies&#39; responses to environmental gradients in distinct ways, despite being highly correlated across species. We also show that incorporating phylogeny into trait-environment models is essential; relying on traits alone would lead to incorrect inferences and predictions of taxa most at risk from warming climates.</description>
  <category>ecology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Systematic comparison of color representations between humans and deep neural networks: towards predicting human color perception in a vast color space</title>
  <dc:creator>Wickramanayaka, N. R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Oizumi, M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The representational structure of human color perception, particularly within vast color spaces, remains incompletely understood. While representational structures for dozens of colors have been studied, exploring structures spanning hundreds or thousands of colors has been infeasible due to the time costs of psychophysical experiments. Given these constraints, deep neural networks (DNNs) have attracted attention as a promising tool for providing proxies or predictions of human perception beyond the scope of psychophysical experiments. However, it remains unclear which DNN models possess internal representations that geometrically align with human color perception. Furthermore, it is unclear which learning paradigm enables DNNs to acquire a color representation that is geometrically aligned with that of humans. Here, we systematically investigate which learning paradigm enables DNNs to produce a color representation that is structurally congruent with that of humans, with a focus on three types: self-supervised learning (SSL) that trains on images alone, supervised learning (SL) that trains on images with category labels, and contrastive language-image pre-training (CLIP) that trains on image-text pairs. We compared internal representations of DNNs with the human similarity judgments of 93 colors using a rigorous unsupervised method termed Gromov-Wasserstein Optimal Transport (GWOT), which reveals whether the representational structures of humans and models align at the fine-item level. Our results show that only the CLIP paradigm acquires color representations that strongly align with human data at the fine-item level. Furthermore, when we leveraged a key advantage of DNNs and investigated a substantial representational structure of 4096 colors, the human-aligned CLIP models consistently converged on a non-trivial distorted ring-like structure, which presents a plausible prediction for the large-scale human color representation. Our work demonstrates an approach for exploring unknown territories of human perception through the use of computational models validated in a limited empirical space, and provides predictions for future large-scale psychophysical experiments.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Equiluminant Border Ownership Cells as a Missing Link in Color Form Perception</title>
  <dc:creator>Mehrani, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tsotsos, J. K.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>We propose the existence of a sub-population of border ownership neurons that signal figure side along equiluminant borders, those defined purely by color contrast. We postulate that these neurons, similar to primate equiluminant V1 [26] and V4 [5] cells, are strongly activated by equiluminant contrast on their preferred side, with diminished response for strictly luminance contrast. To test this hypothesis, we propose a hierarchical and mechanistic model that explains how equiluminant border ownership signals can be achieved in the ventral stream. Our simulation results suggest that model equiluminant neurons are highly color-selective while exhibiting similar orientation and border ownership selectivity as their luminance counterparts. Additionally, our model equiluminant cells indeed exhibited the above postulated pattern of responses. We suggest that these neurons are the missing links in the equiluminance channels in the ventral stream that transform equiluminant oriented edge signals in V1 to equiluminant object-centered shape representations in V4. Our findings point to the importance of re-examining the border ownership neuron population to further detail their role in equiluminant channels in the ventral stream.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Graded BMP signals modulate yellow and red color in fishes impacting adult pigment pattern and behavior</title>
  <dc:creator>Huang, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>de Mello, P. L. H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liu, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liu, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kapadia, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liang, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lu, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Corbo, J. C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Parichy, D. M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Among the most interesting adult traits are those with roles in animal communication. Yet developmental mechanisms by which genes drive cell behaviors in building the final forms of such traits are rarely known. In this context, pigmentation is useful because colors and patterns often provide signals in mate choice, predation avoidance and other behaviors and pigmentation is unusually accessible to observation and manipulation. Here we focus on some of the most prominent signaling colors--red, orange and yellow--and show how BMP signaling at the cellular level allows for a very different kind of signal at the organismal level. Using pearl danio, Danio albolineatus, we find that spatially and temporally graded BMP signals promote development of yellow/orange xanthophores over red erythrophores in the fin of this species and a distantly related minnow, Tanichthys albonubes, and that conserved mechanisms, involving BMP co-receptor Rgmb, regulate differentiation of other pigment cell types in corresponding locations of zebrafish, D. rerio. We further use mutants of D. albolineatus with more red or more yellow cells than wild-type to demonstrate female responsiveness to carotenoid-based color differences between males in shoaling preference assays, and we show the existence of polygenic standing variation for this pigmentary trait. Our findings illustrate a chain of function spanning hierarchical levels and provide a deeper understanding of pigmentary form and function and its evolution.</description>
  <category>developmental biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Damselflies Overcome Color Saturation Barriers of Photonic Glasses via Structural Dispersion and Pigment Loading</title>
  <dc:creator>Lemcoff, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Alus, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Batushansky, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fishman, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Theodor, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shavit, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hyitner, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kelber, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Haataja, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Oron, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Palmer, B. A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Biology&#39;s strategies for manipulating light offer rich inspiration for the design of sustainable replacements to conventional pigments in paints, coatings, and displays. For these applications, where angle-independent color is required, photonic glasses, composed of random arrangements of dielectric spheres, offer a promising solution. However, their intrinsic disorder, particularly from particle polydispersity, fundamentally limits their color saturation and practical utility. In contrast, insects like damselflies and dragonflies exhibit surprisingly vivid, non-iridescent structural colors, despite relying on disordered photonic structures. Here, we show how damselflies combine compositional and structural dispersion to overcome color saturation limits of photonic glasses. Firstly, doping transparent particles with yellow pigments dramatically enhances blue-green structural resonances by the coupled effects of narrowband absorption and refractive index (material) dispersion. Secondly, the refractive index of the nanospheres varies with their size and crystallinity. This gives rise to a &#39;structural dispersion&#39; which maintains consistent optical path lengths in polydisperse assemblies, preserving high color purity. Finally, we show how damselflies tune their structural colors during maturation by precisely modulating the size of the nanospheres. Remarkably, the tuning of particle size, refractive index and pigment loading, arises naturally during the development of the pigment cells - where the pteridine nanospheres undergo a process of densification, crystallization and metabolic maturation.</description>
  <category>animal behavior and cognition</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Egg colour mimicry in the common cuckoo results from coevolutionary alternation, not coevolutionary arms races</title>
  <dc:creator>Hanley, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kepplinger, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nasir, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Samas, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Villa, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>de Alcantara Viana, J. V.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The exquisite eggshell mimicry found in many cuckoo-host systems has been the textbook example of a coevolutionary arms race [1]. In this system, cuckoos lay their eggs in their hosts&#39; nests leaving these foster parents to rear their young [2]. In defence, most of these hosts have evolved the ability to recognize cuckoo eggs. It is long-assumed that these interactions select for ever-improving eggshell mimicry in cuckoo host-races laying distinct eggs that specifically mimic their host&#39;s eggshell, regardless of its particular colour [3,4]. We challenge this paradigm and demonstrate that coevolutionary arms races and egg colour mimicry are the exception to the rule. Here, using eggshell reflectance spectra from 39 host species and the specific cuckoo eggs found in their nests, we show that eggshell colour mimicry is very uncommon even among frequent hosts. Although cuckoo eggs display considerable variation in eggshell colour, their hosts&#39; eggshell colours occupy 6 times their colour volume. As a result, mimicry is only achieved for a small subset of the egg colour gamut. Furthermore, cuckoo host-races rarely lay eggs that match their hosts&#39; eggs better than those of other potential hosts or that are distinct from those laid by other cuckoo host-races. These patterns are inconsistent with the long-held assumption of coevolutionary arms races, but consistent with coevolutionary alternation that is defined by a process of continual host-switching. These findings open new avenues for research in a system that has long served as a model for studying coevolutionary processes.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Spectral tuning and signaling of diverse and most red sensitive visual rhodopsins that drive high colour discrimination in Mantis Shrimp eyes</title>
  <dc:creator>Brouillon, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pushkarev, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lienard, M. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hwang, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Munhoven, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>McDowell, R. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lucas, R. J. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Porter, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sun, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hegemann, P.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Of all visual systems shaped over billions of years, stomatopod crustaceans or mantis shrimps possess arguably one of the most extraordinary eyes, with unmatched potential for broad colour detection (T. W. Cronin &amp; Marshall, 1989; J. Marshall &amp; Oberwinkler, 1999; J. Marshall et al., 2007). Yet how their unusual diversity of visual opsins (Porter et al., 2020) maps onto functional spectral sensitivities (Streets et al., 2022; T. W. Cronin et al., 2022) has remained unresolved. Here, we uncover the molecular rhodopsin-based physiological mechanisms of spectral tuning and show that seventeen opsins, mostly from the colour-sensing midband of the Neogonodactylus oerstedii eye, exhibit distinct spectral absorption ranges and couple to Gq- or Gi-proteins. Two mid-wavelength opsins (NOMs) preferentially absorb blue light, while twelve long-wavelength opsins (NOLs) absorb in the green range. In addition, three NOLs are red-sensitive beyond 600 nm, representing the most far-red-sensitive opsins functionally characterized in animals. Several opsins exhibit photoreversibility with inverse blue-red spectral shifts, revealing an unrecognised layer of photochemical flexibility in stomatopod photoreception. Combined with ommatidial carotenoid filters, our mechanistic model shows how individually tuned rhodopsins shape row-specific spectral sensitivity across the eye, promoting far-red sensitivity in tier 3P in relation to other spectral wavelengths. These specialised rhodopsin-filter combinations collectively enable robust colour vision along a broad light spectrum and across dim and bright conditions, offering new insights into the evolution of one of Natures most sophisticated visual systems.</description>
  <category>biophysics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>charisma: An R package to perform reproducible color characterization of digital images for biological studies</title>
  <dc:creator>Schwartz, S. T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tsai, W. L. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Karan, E. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Juhn, M. S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shultz, A. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>McCormack, J. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Smith, T. B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Alfaro, M. E.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>1. Advances in digital imaging and software tools have provided increasingly accessible datasets and methods for analyzing color evolution. Despite the variety of computational packages available, most rely on color classification before running analyses. Previous methods limit the ability to analyze large-scale image databases, decreases the accuracy of downstream analyses, and is not always representative of biologically relevant color classes. 2. Here, we present charisma, an R package designed to characterize the distribution of distinct color classes in images suitable for large-scale studies of biological organisms. Here, we demonstrate the utility of our package through an analysis of color evolution in a sample of diverse and charismatic birds, tanagers, in the subfamily Thraupinae. 3. We show that charisma can quickly and accurately classify every pixel in an image and validate these results using pre-identified, canonical color swatches. We find that charisma color classifications are consistent with those made by color-pattern experts in the field. Applying charisma to tanager color evolution, we find that charisma outputs seamlessly integrate with downstream evolutionary analyses. 4. Our results demonstrate that using charisma to manually curate and characterize colors in images provides a standardized, reliable, and reproducible framework for high-throughput color classification.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Distinct NIR Reflectance Spectra Associated with Foliar Symptoms of Beech Leaf Disease</title>
  <dc:creator>Moore, E. G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dabydeen, L. C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Salha, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bichler, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Borsuk, A. M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Beech leaf disease (BLD) is an epidemic spreading among American beech (Fagus grandifolia) populations, with characteristic symptoms including dark green, yellow, or brown bands of thickened leaf tissue between secondary veins. Whereas near infrared (NIR) light is reflected by leaf tissue structure, here we used multispectral NIR imaging to distinguish symptomatic from asymptomatic leaf reflectance, as well as to distinguish between different expressions of symptoms (dark green, yellow, and brown bands) within symptomatic leaves. Key findings include significantly higher NIR reflectance in dark green bands of symptomatic tissue compared to asymptomatic tissue ({lambda} = 840, 860, 900, 940, and 980 nm; [~]26.2%, 25.9%, 35.0%, 35.3%, and 32.5% increase respectively). A partial least squares regression model predicted 97% of variation in symptomatic vs. asymptomatic NIR reflectance was attributed primarily to the increase in spongy mesophyll thickness and overall leaf thickness in symptomatic tissue. Water infiltration of the intercellular airspaces in symptomatic and asymptomatic leaves removed differences in NIR reflectance, supporting a mechanistic link between increased NIR reflectance and the foliar symptoms of BLD. Our results highlight the interaction of leaf internal architecture with NIR wavelengths, and informs the development of targeted remote sensing tools, with implications for detecting even early-stage symptoms of BLD.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Chemogenetic modulation of luciferase emission color for imaging and sensing</title>
  <dc:creator>Manirakiza, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shpinov, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gontier, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>El Hajji, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jullien, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gautier, A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Bioluminescent luciferases have emerged as powerful tools for bioimaging, enabling to image biological systems without external excitation light, reducing thus phototoxicity and eliminating background autofluorescence. Advanced imaging requires luciferases that deliver high photon output for enhanced sensitivity, tunable emission colors for multicolor imaging, and red-shifted emission for effective deep tissue imaging. Here, we introduce LumiFAST, a small tunable luciferase engineered by fusing the bright blue-light emitting NanoLuc with the tunable chemogenetic fluorescent reporter pFAST. pFAST binds and stabilizes the fluorescent state of a variety of synthetic fluorogenic chromophores (also called fluorogens). Its proximity with NanoLuc leads to efficient bioluminescence resonance energy transfer (BRET), enabling customizable red-shifted emission. Thanks to the small size of pFAST, LumiFAST maintains a compact structure, while its modular design allows emission color to be tuned from cyan to green, yellow, orange and red simply by changing the fluorogen. Systematic optimization of the fusion topology and linker length yielded an optimal variant with apparent BRET efficiencies reaching up to 90 %. The red-shifted emission of LumiFAST enables dual-color microscopy imaging when used alongside NanoLuc and allows imaging through thick scattering media. Beyond imaging, our insights into the structural factors governing efficient BRET allowed us to engineer biosensors based on NanoLuc and pFAST for the visualization of protease activity and protein-protein interactions in live cells.</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Peculiar Pigment Pattern and Population Profile of a Poisonous Pufferfish</title>
  <dc:creator>Miyazawa, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Doi, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Takahashi, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nishiyama, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shigenobu, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Misawa, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kikuchi, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sakai, H.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Pufferfish are well-known for their toxicity, yet they also exhibit a remarkable diversity of pigment patterns. Mushifugu (Takifugu exascurus) is a pufferfish endemic to Japan&#39;s coastal waters and is characterized by conspicuous labyrinthine patterns. Despite being recorded along both the Sea of Japan and the Pacific coasts, it has a limited distribution and is infrequently observed. Aside from its unique body pattern, mushifugu shows little to no morphological differences from other Takifugu species, often leading to speculation that it may be an interspecific hybrid. In addition, previous theoretical and empirical studies have shown that complex camouflage-like labyrinthine patterns can emerge through the &#39;pattern blending&#39; caused by hybridization between spotted species, providing support for this possibility. Here, we investigate the phylogenetic origin of mushifugu and its distinctive pattern through population structure analysis and demographic inference in comparison with its closest spotted relative, komonfugu (T. flavipterus). Mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) analysis revealed two regional haplogroups within mushifugu--one in the Sea of Japan (SJ) and the other in the Pacific Ocean (PO). In the haplotype network, the SJ haplogroup formed a distinct cluster, whereas the PO haplogroup appeared as its own cluster connected to the komonfugu haplogroup. By contrast, genome-wide SNP analyses indicated limited structure between the SJ and PO mushifugu populations, while clearly separating mushifugu from komonfugu. Coalescent-based demographic inference suggested that the two species diverged following a bottleneck event in the early Pleistocene. These results confirm that mushifugu is a distinct species rather than a recent interspecific hybrid. Nevertheless, evidence of introgression was detected in both mitochondrial and nuclear genomes, suggesting multiple episodes of past hybridization between mushifugu and komonfugu, highlighting the potentially complex evolutionary processes shaping Takifugu species and their pigment patterns.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>MicroRNA166-HD-ZIP III module impacts tuber shape, color and productivity in potato</title>
  <dc:creator>Patil, N. S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Vasav, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kumari, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Arora, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Natarajan, B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Banerjee, A. K.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>MicroRNA165/166 is a highly conserved and abundant microRNA family in plants that targets class III homeodomain leucine zipper (HD-ZIP III) transcription factors. Their essential roles in plant development, organ polarity, meristem maintenance, and vascular differentiation have been well established. However, their role in storage organ development, particularly in potato tuberization remains unknown. Here, we demonstrate the pleiotropic effects of miR166 on potato (Solanum tuberosum spp. Andigena) growth and development. Suppression of miR166 via target mimicry (MIM166) resulted in reduced plant height, altered vascular patterning, diminished leaf curvature, and impaired root development. Remarkably, MIM166 lines produced elongated, pigmented tubers with reduced yield under short-day conditions. Transcriptomic analyses of swollen head versus stalk of tuberizing stolons revealed altered expression of auxin-, cytokinin-, and gibberellin-related genes, consistent with hormone quantification data, suggesting the key role of phytohormones in governing tuber shape. Anthocyanin profiling indicated elevated accumulation of cyanidin 3-glucoside, pelargonidin 3-glucoside, and delphinidin 3-glucoside in MIM166 tuber peels, correlating with the upregulation of anthocyanin biosynthetic genes. Tuber productivity in these lines was reduced possibly due to the decreased expression of SWEET11b and distorted vascular structures in the MIM166 lines. Further, StREVOLUTA, a direct miR166 target, exhibited dynamic expression during stolon differentiation and could modulate the expression of auxin biosynthesis genes. Collectively, our results demonstrate that the miR166-HD-ZIP III module is functional in potato, plays conserved roles in regulating key developmental traits, and is active through early stolon-to-tuber transition stages, affecting tuber shape, color and productivity.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Predictive Networks Generate Motion-Induced Color Illusions</title>
  <dc:creator>Ueda, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sinapayen, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Watanabe, E.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Subjective color (SC) refers to chromatic perception induced by achromatic stimuli, as classically demonstrated using Benham\&#39;s top. Despite nearly two centuries of investigation, the underlying neural mechanisms remain unclear. We developed artificial neural network (ANN) models trained on natural videos using predictive learning to investigate SC generation. These models successfully reproduced artificial subjective color (ASC) despite the absence of explicit color information in the training stimuli. Critically, ASC characteristics were systematically influenced by the colors of moving objects in the training videos. Using progressively simplified stimuli, ranging from natural scenes to 3D computer graphics to 2D animations, we demonstrated that the colors of moving objects are the primary determinant of ASC properties. We propose that predictive learning establishes color associations with motion patterns, causing the arcs on Benham\&#39;s top to be perceived as moving objects with their corresponding colors. These findings suggest that cortical predictive mechanisms may complement retinal processes in generating subjective color phenomena.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Insertion of an invading retrovirus regulates a novel color trait in swordtail fish</title>
  <dc:creator>Haghani, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dodge, T. O.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baczenas, J. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gunn, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>He, Q.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pangburn, W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sood, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Du, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fascinetto-Zago, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kaatmann, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ou, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dougan, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Olmos-Santiago, N. S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Preising, G. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Payne, C. Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Haase Cox, S. K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hunnicutt, K. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Madrzyk, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Moran, B. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Stigloher, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Powell, D. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Schartl, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gifford, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Han, G. z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Schumer, M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>For over a century, evolutionary biologists have been motivated to understand the mechanisms through which organisms adapt to their environments. Coloration and pigmentation are remarkably variable within and between species and can serve as an important window into the mechanisms of adaptation. Here, we map the genetic basis of a newly described iridescence trait in swordtail fish to a single locus. Individuals with this trait appear to sparkle as they move through the water. We find that the trait is driven by the recent endogenization of a retrovirus that inserted near the gene alkal2a. This insertion is associated with changes in the chromatin landscape, upregulation of alkal2a, and accumulation of iridescent cells that adhere to the scales. Rather than causing diseases, our results demonstrate that invading endogenous retroviruses can also regulate novel trait variation in the host. Moreover, we find that this coloration trait may act as an important signal in interactions between fish and their predators in the natural environment.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Anthropogenic factors explain wing colour variation in Colias (Lepidoptera: Pieridae) across the Toronto urbanization gradient</title>
  <dc:creator>Sabatino, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jahner, J. P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>McFarlane, S. E.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Hybridization, or interbreeding between two previously diverged populations, is increasing due to human influences on the environment. Rates of hybridization might be increasing particularly quickly among urban species, especially those that are known to be sensitive to environmental disturbances. Butterflies are one such taxa, as some species are commonly found in urban areas, despite being sensitive indicators. For example, Colias philodice and C. eurytheme (Lepidoptera: Pieridae) hybridize when their ranges are in contact or overlap and are commonly found in large cities throughout North America. However, it is an open question how variation in urbanization might affect variation in hybridization. Using wild Colias across a gradient of urbanization in Toronto, Ontario, we tested how the variation in Colias colour, as an indicator of hybridization, relates to human disturbance and urbanization. We created an objective numeric classification for both C. eurytheme and C. philodice, against which we categorized Colias samples. We found that some of the urbanization metrics, including distance to road, Julian date, and number of pedestrians affect the variation in Colias colour, suggesting that urbanization affects Colias colouration, and potentially rates of hybridization, in Toronto. This means that human disturbance of the environment could be affecting Colias rates of hybridization.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
