<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ColSci publications &amp; preprints</title>
<link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
<atom:link href="https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.20</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Sex-specific doublesex regulation targeting the color-patterning gene h underlies the evolution of wing sexual dimorphism in the harlequin ladybug Harmonia axyridis</title>
  <dc:creator>Yeki, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kato, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Morita, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shimomura, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Niimi, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hinomoto, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Daimon, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>ANDO, T.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Organisms on Earth show various forms of sexual dimorphism, including ornaments, weapon traits, and pheromone glands, which has been acquired through sexual selection during evolution. Although the genetic basis of sexual trait has been investigated in diverse species, its evolutionary origin, evolutionary mode, and evolvability remain poorly understood. To address these issues, we investigated the strain-specific sexual dimorphism in elytral color patterns of the harlequin ladybug, Harmonia axyridis, a species with over 200 color morphs. The most basal Red-nSpots type color morph exhibits sexual dimorphism, whereas other derived color morphs have lost it. To investigate how this loss of sexual dimorphism is associated with the emergence of novel color morphs, we investigated the genetic basis of sexual dimorphism by focusing on the master sex differentiation gene, doublesex (dsx). We show that dsx regulates color pattern dimorphism by negatively modulating black spot size in males. This modulation is primarily mediated by the transcriptional regulation of the color patterning gene, h (Drosophila pannier ortholog). Intraspecific comparative ATAC-seq analysis of the pupal wings revealed that, at the h locus, not the absolute number of Dsx-binding motifs but the proportion of open chromatin regions containing Dsx-binding motifs relative to those lacking such motifs was reduced in strains that had lost sexual dimorphism and acquired novel color patterns, implying that sexual dimorphism evolves based on the balance between novel CREs and Dsx-binding motif density. The present study provides a fundamental molecular framework for understanding how a secondary sexual trait evolves within H. axyridis.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Two mutations in the same MYC-bHLH transcription factor cause segregation of purple coloration of stolons and seed heads in Zoysia japonica x Zoysia matrella F2 and F1 populations</title>
  <dc:creator>Pradhan, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zhao, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Spiekerman, J. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bennetzen, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Khanal, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yu, X.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Milla-Lewis, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Conner, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Schwartz, B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Devos, K. M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Anthocyanins play diverse roles in plants, including attracting pollinators and protecting cells from oxidative damage. In zoysiagrass, a warm season turfgrass, their accumulation in seed heads and stolons can decrease the aesthetic appeal. In this study, a high-density genetic map with ~8000 single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers organized into 20 linkage groups was generated in a Zoysia japonica acc. Meyer x Zoysia matrella acc. PI 231146 F2 population. Using this genetic map, a large-effect quantitative trait locus (QTL) for anthocyanin variation in stolons and seed heads was mapped to chromosome 12 (PP locus). Variant analysis of a candidate gene for PP, Zjn_sc00004.1.g07010.1.sm.mk, which encodes a MYC-bHLH transcription factor that regulates anthocyanin biosynthesis, revealed a SNP at an exon-intron boundary in Meyer that led to intron retention. Interestingly, an F1 population derived from the same parents segregated for seed head color but uniformly displayed purple stolons. Seed head color in the F1 population co-mapped with the PP locus which, combined with genotypic and yeast two-hybrid analyses, revealed that a SNP in PI 231146 leading to an Ala163Ser substitution in the MYB-interacting N-terminal domain of the same MYC-bHLH transcription factor was likely causal. The Ala163Ser substitution affected interaction of MYC-bHLH with MYB in a MYB-dependent manner. The identified mutations can be exploited to develop cultivars with green seed heads and stolons. The high-marker-density interspecific Z. japonica x Z. matrella F2 genetic map also provides a robust tool for identifying genomic regions and genes of agronomic interest that differentiate the two species.</description>
  <category>genetics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Colour and shape evolution reflect ecological specialisation in Pomacentridae</title>
  <dc:creator>Jimenez, A. G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Salamin, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gaboriau, T.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>How ecological pressures shape phenotypic traits such as colouration and morphology is a fundamental question in evolutionary biology. Colouration often mediates functions such as communication, camouflage, and species recognition, while morphological traits influence locomotion, feeding, and habitat use. In reef fishes, both traits exhibit striking diversity, frequently shaped by ecological interactions. The damselfish family (Pomacentridae) exemplifies this variation, displaying a wide range of colouration, morphology, and ecological strategies, including dietary specialisation, mutualistic behaviours, and freshwater tolerance. In this study, we examined 342 Pomacentridae species using an integrative framework that combined colouration and morphometric analyses, ancestral state reconstructions of habitat, diet, and symbiosis, and Phylogenetic Comparative Methods (PCMs). Our goal was to assess how ecological factors have influenced the evolution of phenotypic traits and to identify patterns of convergence linked to ecological specialisation. We found repeated convergent evolution in both colouration and body shape, often associated with similar ecological pressures. Species with specialised diets exhibited consistent morphological adaptations, underscoring the role of trophic ecology in shaping body form. Additionally, we observed a strong association between habitat type and dominant colouration patterns, consistent with a camouflage function. These findings clarify the evolutionary processes driving phenotypic diversity in damselfishes and highlight the importance of ecological adaptation in shaping both morphology and colouration. Our work contributes to a broader understanding of how form and function evolve in response to ecological pressures in coral reef ecosystems.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Retinal pigment epithelium-derived PD-L1 reprograms microglial cells and protects against retinal degeneration in mouse models of experimental AMD and genetic retinitis pigmentosa</title>
  <dc:creator>Su, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wang, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lai, Q.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wang, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liu, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tang, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yu, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Chen, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ma, X.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>HOU, L.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Retinal degeneration is a leading cause of blindness and a significant health burden during aging worldwide. Because of its complex pathogenic mechanisms, however, effective interventions applicable to multiple retinal degenerations remain limited. Excessive microglia-mediated inflammation is a common pathological feature of different retinal degenerative diseases, and inhibiting these overactive inflammatory responses by reprogramming microglia may provide a therapeutic strategy with broad-spectrum potential. Here, we uncover a novel retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) homeostatic signal, PD-L1, that drives the reprogramming of activated microglial toward a retinal-protective phenotype. Using multiple analyses, including gene expression profiling bioinformatics, adeno-associated virus-mediated RPE-specific gene overexpression, pharmacological, and genetic manipulations, we show that RPE cells upregulate the expression of PD-L1 to modulate microglia for protection against retinal degeneration in an experimental dry AMD mouse model. Bioinformatics enrichment analysis of the high-expression gene signatures of subretinal microglia in AMD patients, combined with pharmacological blocking of NF-{kappa}B activity or using Nlrp3 knockout mice, show that PD-L1/PD-1 signaling suppresses NF-{kappa}B activation in microglia, thereby inhibiting NLRP3 inflammasome priming and attenuating microglia-mediated excessive inflammation. Furthermore, the overexpression of PD-L1 by the AAV8 virus exerts similar microglial reprogramming and retinal protective effects to alleviate retinal degeneration in a preclinical model of retinitis pigmentosa. These findings reveal that RPE-derived PD-L1 suppresses inflammatory reprogramming of subretinal microglia and mitigates retinal degeneration, highlighting a promising proof of concept for PD-L1 as a potential therapeutic target for the broad treatment of retinal degenerative diseases.</description>
  <category>genetics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A comparative GWAS of eye colour in light and dark eye genetic backgrounds defined by HERC2 rs12913832 polymorphism</title>
  <dc:creator>Abbatangelo, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lona Durazo, F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Edwards, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Parra, E. J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>rs12913832, a polymorphism located in an enhancer within the HERC2 gene, which is known to regulate OCA2 transcription, is heavily relied upon as a predictor of light versus dark eyes. Individuals with the GG genotype are projected to have blue eyes, while individuals with the AA or AG genotypes are projected to have darker eye colours (primarily brown). However, eye colour is a polygenic trait, and previous studies have revealed that a significant proportion of individuals self-report an eye colour that is not concordant with their genotype at rs12913832. Herein, we address the question: What common markers are influencing eye colour in individuals whose self-reported phenotype does not correspond to the expected phenotype based on their rs12913832 genotype. Building upon our prior investigation of iris pigmentation genetics in individuals with an expected &quot;blue eye&quot; background (rs12913832:GG genotype) in a sample of the Canadian Partnership for Tomorrows Health (CanPath) cohort, this study extends the analysis to include individuals with an expected &quot;brown eye&quot; background (rs12913832:AA+AG). We identified variants in SLC45A2, TYRP1, TYR, SLC24A4 and TSPAN10, which may influence eye colour presentation in individuals with the rs12913832:GG genotype and variants in IRF4, TYRP1 and OCA2, which may influence eye colour presentation in individuals with the rs12913832:AA+AG genotype. These markers include well-known pigmentation-associated single nucleotide polymorphisms, such as rs16891982 (SLC45A2), rs1126809 (TYR), rs12203592 (IRF4), rs1800407 (OCA2) and rs6420484 (TSPAN10). Several of these loci were replicated using independent quantitative eye colour measures, including heterochromia and CIELAB colour dimensions. This research highlights the importance of gene-gene interactions and the polygenic nature of pigmentation traits, emphasizing modifying effects that can sometimes counteract the dominant influence of rs12913832, contributing to advancements in pigmentation genetics and forensic applications.</description>
  <category>genetics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>FLEXTAG: A Small and Self-renewable Protein Labeling System for Anti-fading Multi-color Super-resolution Imaging</title>
  <dc:creator>Zhang, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yao, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wang, X.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tao, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yang, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wang, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liu, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Feric, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zhou, R.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Super-resolution fluorescence imaging enables visualization of subcellular structures and molecular interactions at the nanoscale, but its broader application has been hindered by long-standing limitations in current protein tagging systems, including rapid photobleaching, tag-induced artifacts, poor post-fixation labeling efficiency, and restricted multiplexing capability. Here, we present FLEXTAG (Fluorescent Labeling for Exchangeable, X-resilient Tagging in Advanced Generic Nanoscopy), a comprehensive protein labeling system comprising three orthogonal, ultrasmall (12-18 kDa), and self-renewable protein tags that collectively overcome these major limitations of existing tagging systems, enabling optimized multi-color super-resolution imaging. Through continuous exchange of organic fluorophores, FLEXTAG supports unprecedented durations of high-resolution imaging in both live and fixed cells with minimal photobleaching. It is compatible with major super-resolution modalities, such as SIM, STED, STORM, and PAINT, and is applicable to a wide range of subcellar targets. To further address fixation-induced labeling inefficiency and background fluorescence, we developed a novel protection-based fixation method and chemical blocking strategies that significantly preserve tag accessibility and enhance signal-to-noise ratio, improvements that are broadly applicable to other protein tagging systems. Altogether, FLEXTAG enables long-term tracking of dynamic behaviors and interactions of subcellular targets, as well as mapping of nanoscale protein organizations and cellular architecture, advancing both basic research and translational applications in cell biology.</description>
  <category>bioengineering</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Zika Virus Persistently Infects Retinal Pigment Epithelial Cells, Eliciting Limited Cytopathic Effects and Loss of Epithelial Characteristics Consistent with Epithelial-Mesenchymal Transition.</title>
  <dc:creator>EL SAFADI, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>MOKHTARI, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>LEBEAU, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>VIRANAICKEN, W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>KREJBICH-TROTOT, P.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The Zika virus (ZIKV), a pathogenic member of the orthoflavivirus family, is raising serious health concerns worldwide. Like Dengue (DENV) and Chikungunya (CHIKV) viruses, it is one of the arboviruses that poses an emerging threat to areas where its main vectors, Aedes mosquitoes, proliferate, well beyond tropical and subtropical regions. Although often asymptomatic or mild, ZIKV infection has been responsible for a worrying increase in serious congenital syndromes, including microcephaly. The ability of ZIKV to be transmitted sexually and its long persistence in body fluids suggests its incomplete clearance in particular tissues, linked to recurrent infection. Among its clinical presentations, ZIKV infection has been associated with ocular complications, including maculopathy, retinopathy, uveitis, and optic neuropathy, which can lead to lasting visual impairment. The blood-retinal barrier (BRB), primarily composed of retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) and endothelial cells, plays a crucial role in shielding the retina from pathogens. Its disruption has been linked to viral retinal infections. In vitro monitoring of infection on hTERT RPE-1 cells revealed an ability of ZIKV to persist for up to 30 days in nearly 10% of the cells. This prolonged infection was marked by low cytopathic effects but notable morphological changes throughout the cell layer, suggestive of an epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT). Long-lasting viral replication and production was associated with reduced expression of epithelial genes and increased expression of certain mesenchymal genes, suggesting that integrity of the RPE layer may be compromised. These results indicate that viral persistence and phenotypical transition observed in vitro in RPE cells could provide clues to understanding the late onset of ocular pathophysiological manifestations in Zika virus-related diseases.</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Comprehensive characterization of human color discrimination thresholds</title>
  <dc:creator>Hong, F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bouhassira, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Chow, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sanders, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shvartsman, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Guan, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Williams, A. H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Brainard, D. H.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Discrimination thresholds reveal the limits of human perception; scientists have studied them since the time of Fechner in the 1800s. Forced-choice psychophysical methods combined with the method of constant stimuli or parametric adaptive trial-placement procedures are well-suited for measuring one-dimensional psychometric functions. However, extending these methods to characterize psychometric fields in higher-dimensional stimulus spaces, such as three-dimensional color space, poses a significant challenge. Here, we introduce a novel Wishart Process Psychophysical Model (WPPM) that leverages the smooth variation of threshold across stimulus space. We demonstrate the use of the WPPM in conjunction with a non-parametric adaptive trial-placement procedure by characterizing the full psychophysical field for color discrimination in the isoluminant plane. Each participant (N = 8) completed between 6,000 and 6,466 three-alternative forced-choice (3AFC) oddity color discrimination trials. The WPPM was fit to these trials. Importantly, once fit, the WPPM allows readout of discrimination performance between any pair of stimuli, providing a comprehensive characterization of the psychometric field. In addition, the WPPM readouts were validated for each participant by comparison with 25 probe psychometric functions. These were measured with an additional 6,000 trials per participant that were held out from the WPPM fit. The dataset offers a foundational resource for developing perceptual color metrics and for benchmarking mechanistic models of color processing. This approach is broadly generalizable to other perceptual domains beyond color.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>mScarlet3-H with low brightness and fluorescence lifetime has potential for cellular lifetime-unmixing and lifetime-based pH-sensing applications</title>
  <dc:creator>Gadella, T. W. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>van Weeren, L.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>An independent evaluation of the spectroscopic properties, cellular performance, merits and pitfalls of the red fluorescent protein mScarlet3-H as compared to mScarlet3 is reported. mScarlet3-H was generated from mScarlet3 by a single M163H mutation. Purified mScarlet3-H is characterized by a molar coefficient of 79,040 M-1cm-1, a fluorescence quantum yield of 17.8%, molecular brightness of 14.1 and a heterogeneous multiexponential decay with an average fluorescence lifetime of 1 ns. Evaluation in living mammalian cells revealed a comparable maturation speed and efficiency of mScarlet3 and mScarlet3-H, but the overall cellular brightness of mScarlet3-H was 5-fold lower than that of mScarlet3. Photobleaching analysis in live cells revealed identical photobleaching kinetics of mScarlet3-H and mScarlet-H. The fluorescence intensity, fluorescence spectra and fluorescence lifetime of mScarlet3-H were found to be strongly pH-dependent between pH 4-8. The fluorescence lifetime increased from 1 ns to 3 ns in lowering the pH from 8 to 4 with a pK of ~6. The much lower lifetime of mScarlet3-H (~1 ns) as compared to mScarlet3 (~4 ns) allows dual fluorescence lifetime unmixing applications in single channel FLIM recordings in compartments with neutral to slightly alkaline pH. Furthermore, the strongly pH-dependent fluorescence lifetime of mScarlet3-H enables fluorescence lifetime-based pH sensing in a pH region between pH 5 to 7. Using this property, a pH of 6.5 was measured in the lumen of the Golgi system in living cells and motile endomembrane vesicles revealed pH values between 5.5 and 6. Also autophagy of the cytoplasm can be visualized by the pH-dependent fluorescence lifetime with mScarlet3-H accumulation in lysosomes. Potential useful applications and pitfalls regarding the special properties of mScarlet3-H are discussed.</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>contradictory results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Volitional Attention to Color: Breaking Willed Attention out of the Spatial Domain</title>
  <dc:creator>Nadra, J. G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sullivan, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mangun, G. R.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Attention can be guided by either voluntary (top-down) or involuntary (bottom-up) influences. In real-world vision, voluntary attention can be directed by a wide range of influences such as reward, priming, meaning, experience, selection history, and volition. Laboratory studies of voluntary attention have commonly used attention-directing cues to induce or instruct human subjects to attend one class of stimuli while ignoring others. In recent years, free choice conditions of attention have been introduced, where self-generated volitional shifts of attention (willed attention) are possible (for a review, see Nadra &amp; Mangun, 2023). Prior willed attention studies have focused on mechanisms of covert spatial attention, investigating the neurophysiological correlates of willed attention related to both post-decision processing, and the pre-decision brain activity patterns that predict participants&#39; free choices about where to attend. Much less work, however, has been done on willed non-spatial attention. In this study, in a fashion similar to prior willed spatial attention studies, we investigated willed attention to stimulus color. In a trial-by-trial cueing design, subjects were either cued what color to attend or were allowed to freely choose what color to attend, in order to subsequently discriminate visual features of the cued or willfully chosen target. Behavioral measures showed that the subjects were selectively attending the cued or willed color. Using support vector machine decoding on EEG alpha (8-12 Hz) signals, we found significant post-decision differences in alpha-band power and broadband EEG voltage when participants chose to attend to orange versus purple. However, in contrast to the findings in prior work on willed spatial attention, no pre-decision EEG signals could be identified that predicted which color participants would choose to attend to.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A common mechanism and multiple advantages of pigment loss underlie the convergent evolution of albinism in cave animals</title>
  <dc:creator>Bilandzija, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Renner, K. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cetkovic, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jeffery, W. R.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The loss of pigmentation is a hallmark adaptation of cave-dwelling animals but the underlying mechanisms are poorly understood. This study investigates the cellular and biochemical basis of albinism, the loss of melanin pigment, which convergently evolved across a wide range of cave animals. Is albinism caused by the interruption of pigment synthesis or elimination of the pigment cell lineage? The results suggest that albinism evolved by a common mechanism, a block in the first step of the melanin biosynthesis pathway, the conversion of L-tyrosine to L-DOPA, in diverse albino cave animals ranging from annelids and mollusks to vertebrates. Pigment cells are conserved in all tested albino cave species and distributed in patterns resembling pigmentation in their close surface relatives. The cells capable of melanin synthesis when provided with L-DOPA substrate were detected at the sites of injuries in a cave annelid, cave mollusk, and cave teleost, suggesting roles in innate immunity during tissue repair, which may explain why pigment cells are conserved despite the loss of pigment production. Next, we focused on the longstanding issue of the evolutionary forces involved in the regression of pigmentation in cave animals and explored hypotheses of why losing pigmentation might be adaptive in cave environments. First, we tested the hypothesis that pigment regression may conserve energy, which is important for survival in the food-limited cave environment. Our results indicate that melanin synthesis has a marked energetic cost in the cavefish, Astyanax mexicanus. Lastly, we show that the disruption of melanin synthesis at its first biosynthetic step is correlated with increased dopamine levels in multiple depigmented cavefish populations, including populations that evolved albinism independently. This result supports a widespread tradeoff between the melanin and catecholamine synthesis pathways in A. mexicanus. We conclude that the interruption of the conversion of L-tyrosine to L-DOPA in the synthesis of melanin confers multiple advantages that could serve as targets of natural selection, supporting an adaptive hypothesis for the evolution of albinism in cave animals.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Generalizability of machine learning models for plant traits using hyperspectral reflectance data: The case of maize</title>
  <dc:creator>Xu, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ferguson, J. N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kromdijk, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nikoloski, Z.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Hyperspectral reflectance provides rapid and precise phenotyping of plants in a non-destructive manner both in field and well-controlled settings. The resulting data have been used to devise machine learning (ML) models for paired measurements of different traits in diverse plants and crops. Yet, despite advances in using of hyperspectral data to reliably predict crop traits of interest, there are pressing issues concerning the training of ML models, the aggregation of data from crop field trials, and the generalizability of the models in different prediction settings. We collected hyperspectral reflectance data along with 25 anatomical, gas exchange, and chlorophyll fluorescence traits from 320 recombinant inbred lines of a maize Multi-Parent Advanced Generation Inter-Cross population grown across three consecutive seasons. We use these data to systematically: (1) compare the performance of representative ML models for different traits, including slow fluorescence kinetics whose predictability by hyperspectral data has not yet been investigated, (2) evaluate the ML model performance in prediction scenarios concerning unseen genotypes, unseen seasons, and the combination thereof, (3) investigate the effects of data aggregation of ML model performance. These problems are addressed in a rigorous nested cross-validation setting that provides a template for adequate assessment of performance of ML models for diverse crop traits considering the particularities of the experimental design.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Purification and pigment analysis of diadinoxanthin-binding PSI-LHCI supercomplexes from Euglena gracilis strain Z</title>
  <dc:creator>Sakamoto, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kato, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nakajima, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shen, J.-R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nagao, R.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Euglena gracilis, a phototrophic flagellate, possesses light-harvesting complexes (LHCs) with a pigment composition distinct from that of land plants and green algae, despite notable similarities in LHC polypeptide sequences to green algae. Here, we purified photosystem I-LHCI (PSI-LHCI) supercomplexes from E. gracilis strain Z and characterized their biochemical and spectroscopic properties. The purified complex exhibited a unique pigment profile, notably including diadinoxanthin that is typically found in red-lineage organisms, setting E. gracilis apart from green-lineage organisms. The absorption spectrum displayed the Qy band of chlorophyll a at 675nm, while the 77-K fluorescence-emission spectrum revealed a prominent peak at 732nm, closely resembling those in land plants. These features suggest that long-wavelength chlorophylls bound to LHCI may be evolutionarily conserved. Nevertheless, the absence of neoxanthin, lutein, and violaxanthin further differentiates the Euglena LHCIs from other oxyphototrophs. Together, these results illuminate the evolutionary diversification of PSI-LHCI supercomplexes and offer insights into the unique pigment-binding features of the Euglena light-harvesting system.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Association of iridescence and tails with flight proxies suggests that predation drives convergence in skipper butterflies</title>
  <dc:creator>Linke, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Debat, V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Matos-Maravi, P.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Phenotypic evolution is shaped by phylogenetic, ecological and biomechanical constraints. Butterfly wings offer an ideal system to explore these constraints as their evolution is strongly influenced by natural and sexual selection affecting colour patterns and wing shape in relation to visual signalling and flight performance. We focus on Eudamina skippers, butterflies with large-scale phenotypic convergences involving wing shape and colour pattern. Using a comprehensive morphometric dataset encompassing 176 species, we assess their morphological evolution in a phylogenetic framework. We show that hindwing tails and dorsal iridescence, proposed to signal high escape ability, have repeatedly evolved in tropical species. Hindwing tails are associated with intermediate body size, low wing loading and a forewing shape that facilitates manoeuvrability; iridescence is more common in large species with significantly high wing loading and aspect ratio, indicating high flight speed and manoeuvrability. The evolution of all tested morphometric traits is best described by Ornstein-Uhlenbeck models, indicating stabilising selection around fitness optima in Eudamina. Models testing for random drift or early burst dynamics were rejected in all cases. We reveal a clear co-evolution between the fore- and hindwing shapes, despite both wings having different functional constraints. Hindwing tails have a significant recurrent effect on forewing shape in lineages evolving them independently, suggesting the existence of evolutionary trade-offs between flight performance and antipredator defences. Our study shows that the convergent morphologies across Eudamina have likely arisen not by neutral evolution but by ecological selection influenced by biomechanical constraints.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Monitoring Forest Foliar Moisture Using Sentinel-2 Reflectance and Radiative Transfer Model Inversion</title>
  <dc:creator>Kotzur, I.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Boer, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yebra, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Moore, B. D.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Foliar moisture content (FMC) of forests canopies is important for understanding biodiversity, including animal habitat quality for forest-dependent fauna and forest fire risk. In this study, we modelled spatiotemporal variation in FMC using optical remote sensing. We inverted the PROSPECT and GEOSAIL Radiative Transfer Models (RTM) on Sentinel-2 satellite reflectance data of 20 m ground resolution to retrieve FMC, and then predicted FMC at sub-continental scales using a random forest (RF) regression emulation of the RTM model. An RTM look-up-table, from earlier work, was filtered by ecological criteria from 24 sites sampled along precipitation and canopy cover gradients and was inverted by using the spectral angle, as a merit function. The RF emulator allowed efficient computation and presentation of an extensive and fine-scale forest FMC data cube of interest in animal, fire and plant ecology. Our RTM-based, predictions of forest and woodland FMC had a root mean square error (RMSE) of 19.9% of dry matter content and explained more than 60% of variance (r2 = 0.62). This represents an improvement over previous models using reflectance data of coarser spatial resolution, particularly in terms of explained variance (r2=0.17 and RMSE=32%). The emulator model achieved similar performance to the RTM with slightly larger error (RMSE = 21.77%) and smaller explained variance (r2 = 0.54). Overall, both models performed best in forests, and woodlands of moderate to high canopy density (&gt; ~0.75 LAI). This study demonstrates that FMC can be monitored at spatial resolutions that allow intra- or inter-landscape patterns to be resolved surpassing previous capabilities.</description>
  <category>ecology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bird species with color polymorphism have greater ecological success</title>
  <dc:creator>Kazuya, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sato, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sekercioglu, C. H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Noriyuki, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Takahashi, Y.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The explanation of the variation in ecological success of species is one of the key challenges in ecology, evolutionary biology and conservation biology. Here, we discuss the function of polymorphism in body color which is one of the most conspicuous features of organisms strongly affecting the performance of species. We applied a phylogenetic comparative approach to assess whether body color polymorphisms contribute to species success in birds, reflected in distributional ranges, extinction risk, and current population trends. We compiled and analyzed a comprehensive global dataset that included the distribution, phylogeny, ecology and morphological traits of all extant bird species. Species with body color polymorphism showed larger distributional ranges, larger environmental ranges, lower risk of extinction, and more stable population trends. Our analyses suggest that the presence of color polymorphism contributes to avian species success at the global scale, especially reflected in lower extinction likelihood and better population trends.</description>
  <category>ecology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hawkmoths learn best without negative reinforcement in a differential colour association task</title>
  <dc:creator>Manel, A. N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Foster, J. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Stöckl, A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Visual learning in insects can be strongly influenced by the underlying context and conditions. Improved colour learning has been demonstrated using differential conditioning with reward-aversion paradigms in insects like wasps, bumblebees, and honeybees, where substances that induce strong aversion, such as quinine, enable more accurate discrimination. Although learning outcomes of differential conditioning are closely tied to the perceived reward and aversion, few studies have compared the role of negative reinforcements in shaping associations, and their relevance across insect groups. In our study, we compare the role of aversive substances for differential in the hummingbird hawkmoth, Macroglossum stellatarum, a diurnal moth that relies on vision for foraging. Tying to previous learning studies in insects, we paired a sugar-rewarded target with a distractor that was paired with either quinine, salt, citric acid, water, or was presented with no aversive substance. Learning outcomes were compared by inverting a strong colour preference between perceptually close or distant colour pairs, to provide tasks with disparate challenges. Contrary to results from other insect species, we found that moths trained with quinine were worse at switching preferences between similar colours compared to training with citric acid and appetitive-only differential conditioning. We also show that quinine interferes with sucrose perception, potentially impairing target acquisition during training. Additionally, we link differences in learning arising from the negative reinforcements to their impact on exploration during foraging. Our results highlight the role of experience in modulating behaviour and discuss the importance of interpreting learning outcomes based on an animal&#39;s sensory ecology and foraging dynamics.</description>
  <category>animal behavior and cognition</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mechanism of PMC (2,2,5,7,8-pentamethyl-6-chromanol), a sterically hindered phenol antioxidant, in rescuing oxidized low-density lipoprotein-induced cytotoxicity in human retinal pigment epithelial cells</title>
  <dc:creator>Chaudhary, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Moon, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hu, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kriukov, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pestun, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baranov, P. Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ng, Y.-S. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Damore, P. A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Geographic atrophy or late stage dry age-related macular degeneration (AMD) is characterized by drusen deposition and progressive retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) degeneration, leading to irreversible vision loss. The formation of drusen leads to dyshomeostasis, oxidative stress and irreversible damage to RPE. In this study, we used an in vitro model of oxidized-low density lipoproteins (ox-LDL) induced human RPE damage/death model to investigate the mechanism whereby a sterically hindered phenol antioxidant compound, PMC (2,2,5,7,8-pentamethyl-6-chromanol) protects RPE against ox-LDL-induced damage. We show that PMC exerts its protective effect by preventing the upregulation of stress-responsive heme oxygenase-1 (HMOX1/HO-1) and NAD(P)H:quinone oxidoreductase (NQO1) at mRNA and protein levels. This effect was due to PMC mediated blockade of ROS generation, which in turn blocked nuclear translocation of the Nuclear factor erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2) transcription factor, ultimately preventing the upregulation of antioxidant response elements (ARE), including HMOX1 and NQO1. A key role for HO-1 was demonstrated when the protective effect of PMC was inhibited by the knockdown of HMOX1. Additionally, treatment of PMC under different experimental conditions and time points revealed that the continuous presence of PMC is required for optimal protection against ox-LDL-induced cytotoxicity, defining the cellular pharmacokinetics of the molecule. Our data demonstrate the involvement of a key antioxidant pathway through which PMC mitigates oxidative stress induced by ox-LDL and provides a potential therapeutic strategy to suppress RPE degeneration/damage during AMD progression.</description>
  <category>molecular biology</category>
  <category>confirmatory results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sustained Lysosomal Delivery of Enhanced Cy3-Labeled Acid Nanoparticles Restores Lysosomal pH in Retinal Pigment Epithelial Cells and Astrocytes</title>
  <dc:creator>Li, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wang, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lu, W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jishkariani, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tsourkas, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kaja, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nair, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dunaief, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mitchell, C. H.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Lysosomal pH is frequently elevated in age-dependent neurodegenerations like Age-related Macular Degeneration (AMD), Alzheimer&#39;s Disease (AD), and Parkinson&#39;s Disease (PD). Tools that restore lysosomal pH to an optimal acidic range could enhance enzymatic degradation and reduce waste accumulation. Acidic nanoparticles offer a promising strategy for restoring lysosomal function, but accurate tracking of organelle delivery and long-term retention is needed to optimize dosage. To improve detection and enhance delivery, nanoparticles were synthesized from Poly(D,L-lactide-co-glycolide) (PLGA) polymers covalently linked to the fluorescent Cyanine3 amine (Cy3) probe. Nanoparticle concentration and loading times were optimized to achieve &gt;90% delivery to lysosomes in cultured induced pluripotent stem cell-derived retinal pigment epithelial (iPS-RPE) cells. Uptake was heterogeneous, varying between adjacent cells. Once loaded into lysosomes, the nanoparticles were stably retained, with no detectable changes in concentration, distribution, or size for at least 28 days. iPS-RPE cells internalized more nanoparticles than the ARPE-19 cell line or mouse optic nerve head astrocyte cultures. Functionally, PLGA nanoparticles restored an acidic pH and cathepsin D levels in compromised lysosomes. In summary, Cy3-PLGA nanoparticles enabled improved tracking and long-term delivery to lysosomes, supporting future in vivo applications to restore lysosomal pH in aging and degenerating tissues.</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>ttc39bl, one of the two duplicated paralogs of the tetratricopeptide repeat domain 39B gene, is essential for carotenoid coloration in medaka (Oryzias latipes) and is the gene responsible for the r locus.</title>
  <dc:creator>Kimura, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Inoue, I.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Body color plays key roles in fitness, communication with others, and hiding. In poikilothermal vertebrates, the body color is mainly determined by types and distributions of chromatophores. Among them, carotenoid color of xanthophores/erythrophores is important for interspecific diversity and colorful males as sexual dimorphism. Most vertebrates cannot synthesize carotenoids in their bodies and must ingest them from food. However, the genes involved in the uptake process are not fully understood. Therefore, we tried to identify the causal gene of the carotenoid color mutant of medaka. The HdrR-II1 strain used in the genome project has orange body color in males and white body color in females. The orange and white body color was known to be controlled by the sex-linked R locus, but the causal gene of this was unknown. In this study, we identified that the causal gene of the R locus is tetratricopeptide repeat domain 39b like (ttc39bl). In the HdrR-II1, the ttc39bl on the Y chromosome is normal, but the ttc39bl on the X chromosome has an 821 bases insertion in exon 3 and is broken. This insertion is also present on both the X and Y chromosomes of commercially available white medaka.</description>
  <category>zoology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
