<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ColSci publications &amp; preprints</title>
<link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
<atom:link href="https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.9.20</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Urbanization drives parallel shifts in morphology and colouration of Pieris rapae across three cities</title>
  <dc:creator>McManus, C. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Koski, M. H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Spigler, R. B.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Urbanization is a major driver of global environmental change, yet the evolutionary consequences for natural populations remain poorly understood. The cabbage white butterfly, Pieris rapae, is one of few butterfly species that thrives in cities, offering a unique opportunity to investigate whether urbanization drives parallel phenotypic evolution. In this study, we quantified phenotypic divergence between urban and non-urban populations across three independent metropolitan regions (Cleveland, Philadelphia, and Pittsburgh, U.S.), measuring body size, flight morphology, and wing pigmentation and reflectance in &gt;500 field-caught individuals from 19 sites. Across regions, we found repeated reductions in overall body size and relative thorax mass in urban butterflies of both sexes, along with reduced relative forewing area in urban males, suggesting sex-specific impacts on mobility. Wing pigmentation showed limited urban-associated variation, but we detected novel sexual dimorphism in near-infrared reflectance within urban populations. Together, these results demonstrate repeatable divergence between urban and non-urban butterfly populations across multiple trait axes and suggest that plastic responses to urban stressors previously documented in experimental work manifest as consistent phenotypic shifts in natural populations.</description>
  <category>ecology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tracking Transgenes with Color: RUBY as a Visual Marker in CRISPR-Edited Mutant Plants in Two Triticum Species</title>
  <dc:creator>Kumar, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Palayur, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lunde, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Krasileva, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Milner, M. J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>CRISPR-Cas9 is a powerful tool for precise genome editing in plants, but the presence of foreign DNA, such as T-DNA, raises regulatory concerns and complicates mutant screening and field studies of edited material. Detecting plants with good transgene expression and later removing the T-DNA from edited plants is both time-consuming and costly. To address this, we developed a system that uses the non-destructive RUBY reporter, linked to the CRISPR-Cas9 cassette, and expressed under the ZmUbi1 promoter. To assess the applicability of the system, it was tested on two Triticum species, targeting three genes in either tetraploid or hexaploid wheat. Strong correlations were observed in both T0 and T1 plants between betalain content and Cas9 expression, allowing for the quick identification of plants likely to be edited. Furthermore, the RUBY reporter could be used to select against the transgenic CRISPR-Cas9 cassette in subsequent generations at both the seed and seedling stages, thereby reducing the number of plants that need to be screened to identify edited lines without a T-DNA. This approach, using a nondestructive reporter, enabled rapid distinction between transgene expression in primary transgenics and served as a negative selection in the T1 generation, streamlining selection towards edited and T-DNA-free progeny.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Repeated evolution of convergent iridescence in closely-related species of Morpho butterflies living in sympatry</title>
  <dc:creator>Ledamoisel, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Debat, V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Llaurens, V.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The evolution of visual traits in closely-related species living in sympatry is highly influenced by their ecological interactions: while sexual selection tends to promote the divergence of visual cues involved in mate choice, natural selection via predation may promote the convergence of dissuasive signals between prey species, especially in unpalatable or evasive prey. Here, we investigate the impact of sympatry on the evolution of the blue structural colouration in the wings of two closely-related Morpho butterfly species across several localities throughout Central and South America. Dorsal iridescence might affect mate choice and species recognition, which should promote its local divergence among species. However, the bright flashes and dynamic colour patterns produced by iridescence during flight might also increase survival by confusing predators and favouring escape. Such an effect might in turn lead to convergence in wing iridescence between evasive species occurring in sympatry, a phenomenon dubbed evasive mimicry. To test the effect of these putative antagonistic selective forces on visual cues evolution, we quantified the variation of the structural blue colour displayed at 13 different combinations of illumination/observation angles, on the wings of two closely-related Morpho species. We contrasted 10 sympatric and 11 allopatric locations and specifically compared the phenotypic distances between individuals from different species. Phenotypic distances between heterospecific pairs of individuals were significantly smaller in sympatry, consistent with the hypothesis of a local convergence of iridescence due to evasive mimicry. Interestingly, sexual dimorphism was found between males and females, suggesting that the trade-off between natural and sexual selection on the evolution of iridescence might differ between sexes. Our results suggest that local predation pressures may promote repeated evolutionary convergence of structural colouration between evasive prey species living in sympatry.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Predation and the Evolution of Island Bird Plumage Colouration: Experimental Insights from Island and Mainland Environments</title>
  <dc:creator>Leitao, A. V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Alonso Moya, C. D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lopes, R. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ponti, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Covas, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Doutrelant, C.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Islands serve as natural laboratories for exploring evolutionary processes, often fostering unique species through their isolation and distinct ecological conditions. These environments present opportunities to study how a range of selective pressures shape biodiversity. Bird plumage colouration is one trait that has shown to consistently change in island populations, and predation has been hypothesized to influence these differences. While animals often face a trade-off between signalling to conspecifics and avoiding detection by predators, the role of predation in shaping conspicuousness remains underexplored experimentally. In this study, we asked how predation pressure differs between insular and mainland habitats, and whether predation risk covaries with conspicuousness of male and female birds across environments. In a field experiment, we investigated predation rates using 3D-printed models painted to represent both sexes of 12 bird species from three archipelagos (Madeira, Azores, and Canary Islands) and their closest mainland relatives. These models were deployed in the species&#39; natural environments to measure hit rates (a proxy for predation risk), accounting for factors that influence prey detectability, such as colour of the models, background contrast, and vegetation. We found that models on the islands experienced less hits compared to those on the mainland, while sexual dichromatic models were more likely to be dislodged on the mainland. In addition, for mainland sites, increased chromatic contrast correlated with a higher probability of dislodgment, suggesting that more conspicuous models were more likely to be hit. These results highlight that while predation constrains conspicuousness, other ecological and evolutionary factors likely drive the reduced plumage colouration observed in island birds. Our research offers experimental insights into how predation interacts with conspicuous traits in shaping plumage colouration in birds.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Peroxisome dysfunction alters metabolism of photoreceptor outer segments in human retinal pigment epithelium</title>
  <dc:creator>Mouzaaber, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Feldman, C. B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Huguenin, S. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Han, J. Y. S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Trombly, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zhang, Q.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Rieger, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hojjat, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Huynh, B. C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Misaghi, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Radziwon, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fufa, T. D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hufnagel, R. B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Miller, J. M. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Benson, M. D.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Purpose: Peroxisomes are ubiquitous organelles that compartmentalize metabolic reactions including lipid catabolism and cellular detoxification. Biallelic loss-of-function variants in genes responsible for peroxisome assembly and function cause peroxisome biogenesis disorders (PBDs). Approximately three-quarters of PBDs are due to pathogenic variants in PEX1 or PEX6 and result in multisystem disease, including retinal degeneration and blindness. Despite retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) dysfunction and retinal degeneration occurring frequently in PBDs, precisely how impaired peroxisome activity disrupts retinal function remains to be fully explored. To address this, we differentiated PEX1 knockout (PEX1-/-), PEX6 knockout (PEX6-/-), and wildtype human induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) into RPE to study the consequences of peroxisome dysfunction in this disease-relevant cell type. Methods: CRISPR/Cas9-mediated genome editing was used to generate PEX1-/- and PEX6-/- in human iPSCs. The knockouts and isogenic wildtype iPSCs were differentiated into RPE (iRPE) and characterized by morphology, pigmentation, transepithelial electrical resistance (TEER), and expression of proteins associated with differentiated RPE using immunofluorescence microscopy and flow cytometry. Immunoblot analysis of whole iRPE lysates was used to evaluate the proteolytic processing of peroxisome enzymes, a measure of the integrity of peroxisome matrix protein import. Immunofluorescence detection of peroxisome membrane proteins was used to determine the abundance of peroxisomes across iRPE lines. Targeted lipidomics by gas and liquid chromatography with mass spectrometry were used to quantitatively compare the profiles of wildtype, PEX1-/-, and PEX6-/- iRPE. Accumulation of intracellular neutral lipid, and more specifically lipid droplets, in iRPE was measured using flow cytometry and perilipin-2 immunoblotting, respectively. Phagocytosis of photoreceptor outer segments (POS) by iRPE was evaluated using rhodopsin immunoblotting. Results: PEX1-/-, PEX6-/-, and wildtype iRPE all had comparable hexagonal morphology and integrity of tight junctions, developed pigment, and similarly expressed proteins characteristic of RPE. Immunoblot analysis demonstrated aberrant processing of ACOX1, MFP2, and ACAA1 in PEX1-/- and PEX6-/- iRPE, suggesting impaired peroxisome matrix protein import. Targeted lipid profiling, including total fatty acid (FA) lipid profile analysis, revealed that in comparison to wildtype, PEX1-/- and PEX6-/- iRPE had significantly reduced docosahexaenoic acid (C22:6{omega}3) (p&lt;0.001) and phosphoethanolamine plasmalogens (p&lt;0.0001 for C18:0(plasm)-Total-PE), while very long-chain fatty acids (VLCFA) (p&lt;0.001 for C26:0 and p&lt;0.01 for C26:1{omega}9) and branched-chain FAs (p&lt;0.01 for both pristanic acid and phytanic acid) were significantly elevated. Following a POS challenge, wildtype iRPE had significantly elevated eicosapentaenoic acid (C20:5{omega}3) (p=9.3E-5) and arachidonic acid (C20:4{omega}6) (p=0.013), both retroconversion products from the two most abundant polyunsaturated FAs in POS: C22:6{omega}3 and docosapentaenoic acid (C22:5{omega}6). PEX1-/-and PEX6-/- iRPE accumulated twice the amount of C22:5{omega}6 (p&lt;0.05) relative to wildtype iRPE following a POS challenge, without a significant increase in C20:5{omega}3 or C20:4{omega}6, suggesting impaired {omega}3 and {omega}6 retroconversion pathways. Finally, PEX1-/-and PEX6-/- iRPE demonstrated delayed degradation of internalized POS based on rhodopsin immunoblotting, increased intracellular lipid droplets, and reduced TEER following a POS challenge. Conclusions: Our work has established the first human iRPE models to study the effects of peroxisome dysfunction in the RPE. Impaired peroxisome activity resulted in significant lipid profile changes and defective phagocytosis in iRPE. Dysregulated POS metabolism in the RPE is a potential mechanism driving retinal degeneration in patients with PBDs. Fully understanding the role of peroxisomes in the RPE will facilitate the development of novel therapies for degenerative retinal disorders.</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Syntaxin-3 regulates Tight Junction Assembly in Human Retinal Pigment Epithelium</title>
  <dc:creator>Ramesh, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sivagurunathan, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baburajan, N. V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Chidambaram, S.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) consists of polarized epithelial cells, serving as a support system for photoreceptor maintenance, where the polarity is contributed by the distribution of syntaxins (STX) within the cell. STX3, a known regulator of apical trafficking in epithelial cells, was previously understood to be absent in human RPE cells, with its functions thought to be compensated by STX1A. However, our results on SNARE mRNA expression profile in RPE detected the presence of 2 splice variants of STX3. Further investigation in donor retina, primary hRPE, and ARPE-19 cells revealed detectable levels of STX3 mRNA and protein. STX3 knockdown in ARPE19 resulted in a significant reduction of tight junction (TJ) proteins, compromising TJ assembly, highlighting the critical role of STX3 in maintaining RPE integrity. In addition, immunoprecipitation followed by LC-MS/MS analysis revealed that STX3 and STX1A have a distinct novel protein interactome in RPE. This study identified unique and shared interactants for STX3 and STX1A, suggesting a broader role for RPE beyond its traditional photoreceptor support function. This further emphasises the biological significance of STX1A and STX3 in maintaining retinal homeostasis, which could facilitate the development of novel therapeutic strategies for retinal disorders.</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>contradictory results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A cryptic hybrid zone reveals the genomic basis of flower colour variation in a plant with a large and complex genome</title>
  <dc:creator>Salvado, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gibert, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Chaib, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Raviglione, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bertrand, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>El Baidouri, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mariault, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Llauro, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cravero, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dufau, I.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Marande, W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Carpentier, M.-C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Martin, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Quelennec, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gaultier, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lewin, J.-M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Aymerich, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hinoux, V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bertrand, J. A. M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Flower colour is known to be an automatic magic trait, undergoing divergent selection pressures exerted by distinct pollinators and involved in reproductive isolation. However, variation at this trait may also results from other eco-evolutionary factors whose interpretation requires throughout context-specific analyses. Here, we investigated the eco-evolutionary causes of pink- and yellow-flowered morphs in Pedicularis comosa where their parapatric ranges form a contact zone: in the East of the Pyrenees Mountains. First, we generated a near-chromosome-scale reference genome assembly for this species. We then used a Genotyping By Sequencing approach to infer patterns of genetic diversity and differentiation between populations and morphs at a total of 158 individuals from 11 localities. We found that neutral genetic structure is primarily consistent with geography rather than with colour. However, admixture analyses and clines suggest the existence of a cryptic hybrid zone between morphs. Outlier detection methods and examination of locus-by-locus cline features, then allowed to pinpoint candidate loci to explain colour variation. To gain insight into the functional aspects of these loci, we finally analysed floral transcriptomes and quantified pigments using Liquid Chromatography coupled with Mass Spectrometry (LC-MS) and confirmed the involvement of key genes in the anthocyanin metabolic pathway (e.g. DFR, FLS) and associated pigments (e.g. cyanidin and delphinidin). Our results show that implementing a highly integrative multi-omic approach can allow unraveling the genetic basis and the eco-evolutionary significance of adaptive traits with even very limited previous knowledge, on species with large and complex genomes.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Quantitative muscle color as a proxy for structural and functional characteristics during muscle remodeling in Gryllus lineaticeps</title>
  <dc:creator>Laturney, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Martins, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Diaz, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lo, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Uen, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Williams, C. M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Understanding the cellular and physiological mechanisms underlying muscle remodeling requires model systems that allow rapid, reliable, and quantitative assessment of muscle state. The cricket Gryllus lineaticeps naturally undergoes non-pathological striated muscle breakdown (histolysis), making it a promising system for studying this process. However, current assessments of muscle state are largely qualitative, subjective, and poorly standardized across experiments. Here, we developed and validated a continuous, quantitative muscle color metric to objectively capture histolysis progression and functional changes in muscle. We show that this metric robustly tracks variation in muscle color across remodeling stages, including the challenging fully transparent stage, and strongly predicts protein content, mitochondrial abundance, and iron content in a muscle- and trait-specific manner. The reproducibility of these relationships across independent datasets demonstrates the generality and robustness of this approach. By providing a rapid, objective, and biologically informative proxy of muscle state, this framework not only advances the utility of G. lineaticeps as a model for muscle remodeling but also offers a strategy for exploring the cellular dynamics underlying age-related muscle diseases and disorders, addressing an increasing public health concern in aging populations.</description>
  <category>physiology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>From Sensory Details to Verbal Codes: Visual Memory Reinstatement of Location and Color Features</title>
  <dc:creator>Wang, X.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Becker, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Rahman, R. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Davis, S. W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cabeza, R.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Successful episodic memory depends on the reinstatement of encoding content and processes during retrieval. However, it remains unclear how such reinstatement (1) differs for various perceptual features, (2) supports subjective versus objective memory retrieval, and (3) relies on linguistic information. To investigate these three issues, we designed an fMRI study in which participants encoded and recalled the colors and spatial locations of object pictures, and provided subjective vividness and objective precision measures. We used encoding-retrieval similarity (ERS) to identify feature-level reinstatement for location or color features, and trial-specific reinstatement for individual location trials or individual color trials. The study yielded three main findings. First, feature-level reinstatement in frontoparietal and visual regions supported both location and color memory, whereas trial-specific reinstatement in early visual cortex contributed to location memory and feature-level reinstatement in lateral/anterior temporal cortices, to color memory. Second, trial-specific reinstatement in early visual cortex supported both location vividness and precision, while feature-level reinstatement in inferior frontal gyrus contributed to color vividness, and trial-specific reinstatement in posterior inferior temporal gyrus (including the color area), to color precision. Finally, color name richness (the number of names associated with a particular color) enhanced color memory precision and modulated trial-specific color reinstatement in right anterior inferior temporal gyrus. Together, these findings suggest that perceptual and linguistic reinstatement play complementary roles in visual episodic memory: perceptual replay provides fine-grained sensory details, whereas linguistic replay can scaffold and refine these representations, especially for features that are easier to verbalize such as colors.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Modulation of Avian Iridescence via Malanogenesis</title>
  <dc:creator>Barbosa, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bittner, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Arbore, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Araujo, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pereira, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Andrade, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fekete, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Afonso, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Afonso, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Amorim, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Marques, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nicolai, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Carita, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Brejcha, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lopes, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Alves, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cruz, F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gomez-Garrido, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zamarreno, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gut, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Alyoto, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ali, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hilpert, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hech, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Spiecker, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zubiri, B. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ito, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wakamatsu, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Andersson, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Corbo, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Vogel, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Carneiro, M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The iridescent colors of birds originate in nanoscale feather structures that interact with light. Although the physical principles governing avian iridescence are well-established, the molecular mechanisms assembling these nanostructures into photonic materials remain unknown. Here, we investigate the genetic and developmental basis of iridescence by analyzing mutations from peafowl domestication and color variation in wild birds. We show that melanogenesis governs diverse geometric aspects of feather photonic nanostructures, enabling gains, shifts, and losses in iridescence. Mutations altering melanin composition collapse multilayered photonic systems and yield non-iridescent tissues, while alterations to melanosome abundance, elongation, or deposition timing generate multilayer architectures of variable periodicity and striking color differences. Notably, transitions from non-iridescent to iridescent plumage can arise from single-nucleotide mutations in melanogenic genes, revealing that minimal genetic change can prompt feathers to organize photonic structures. These results demonstrate that the nanoscale order underlying iridescence is developmentally plastic, emerging from physicochemical self-assembly responsive to the biochemical environment rather than from genetically encoded spatial cues. Single-cell transcriptomes from wild species further uncovered extensive melanocyte-centered regulatory rewiring associated with iridescence. Our findings identify melanogenesis as a key pathway for evolving structural coloration and illustrate how genetic programs harness self-organizing processes to generate biological diversity.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A 14-Color Blue-Violet Laser Restricted Full Spectrum Flow Cytometry Panel for Comprehensive Immunophenotyping of Pulmonary Inflammation in Mouse Bronchoalveolar Lavage Fluid</title>
  <dc:creator>Mara, A. B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Miller, J. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ozyck, R. G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hunte, M. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tulman, E. R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Szczepanek, S. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Geary, S. J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Here we describe a 16-parameter, 14-color surface staining panel optimized for murine bronchoalveolar lavage cells that enables reproducible identification of major innate and adaptive immune populations relevant to pulmonary infections or other inflammatory conditions of the airways. The panel enables confident identification of neutrophils, eosinophils, B cells, T cells and subtypes, NK cells, and distinguishes between tissue resident and monocyte-derived macrophages populations. The panel was carefully designed for BAL samples that vary in cell number, are rich in debris, and often autofluorescent. Antibody concentrations are optimized to provide reproducible results regardless of sample-variable cell numbers allowing for the preparation of a single antibody cocktail master mix and rapid sample staining time, thereby cutting down on sample preparation and optimizing cell viability of analyzed samples. The panel facilitates robust cross-sectional and longitudinal comparison of airway inflammation across different airway inflammatory conditions, infections by different respiratory pathogens, impact of vaccination or therapeutics on the inflammatory landscape, and more. It facilitates hypothesis generation by revealing recruitment kinetics and remodeling of myeloid compartments, supports downstream sorting for transcriptomic or functional assays, and provides a standardized baseline for labs to adopt or extend for activation or intracellular cytokine analyses. We have successfully utilized this panel to identify differential host responses to different respiratory Mycoplasma pathogens as well as to longitudinally track the progression of inflammatory response to Mycoplasma pneumoniae over a 21-day time course study. This panel provides an economic immunophenotyping option by utilizing only 14 markers and a two laser (Blue and Violet) full spectrum cytometer to provide comprehensive immunophenotyping power of both myeloid and lymphoid cells. Furthered by lacking the requirement for advanced unmixing for sample analysis, the panel can be easily adopted by the community, enabling comparative meta-analyses of host responses across murine respiratory infection models.</description>
  <category>immunology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rare shell colours in bivalves reveal multiple evolutionary pathways to blue and green colouration</title>
  <dc:creator>Ingram, A. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Razzell Hollis, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Williams, S. T.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Green and blue are rare colours in bivalve shells. Where such colours occur, it is unclear whether they result from shared pigments across taxa, as similar appearances may arise from different compounds and are not necessarily homologous. Identifying their biochemical basis is therefore crucial to understanding the evolution and possible metabolic costs of these unusual traits. We used Raman spectroscopy to analyse resin-embedded cross-sections of valves from 15 bivalve species with green or blue shells. Species represented diversity in shell colour in terms of both phylogeny and morphological traits, including colour location (organic periostracum, organic layers in the calcareous shell or inorganic calcareous matrix). Green colour consistently occurred in organic layers rather than calcareous shell, while blue colour occurs in both calcareous shell and organic layers. Blue colour appears to be due to carotenoid-based pigments, similar to other pigments observed in bivalve shells. Green colour, however, is due either to novel pigments, not previously identified in mollusc shells, which are only weakly Raman active or nanostructures that produce structural colour in the absence of green pigments. Within bivalves, to date structural colour has been reported only in one genus, underscoring its evolutionary significance.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Colour preference and constancy in the giant Asian honey bee Apis dorsata</title>
  <dc:creator>Sudeep, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bhaskar, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Somanathan, H.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Tropical pollinators forage in environments where floral resources vary in space and time, requiring flexible strategies to optimise foraging efficiency. One such strategy, floral constancy - the temporary restriction to a single flower type - strongly influences foraging success and plant-pollinator interactions. We aimed to: (1) quantify spontaneous colour preferences and constancy in the Asian giant honeybee Apis dorsata, (2) test whether reward concentration modulates these preferences, (3) evaluate how quickly learned associations override spontaneous biases, (4) determine whether bees can use multiple colour associations simultaneously, and (5) assess whether local floral spectral patterns correlate with bee preferences. Bees trained to a neutral UV-grey stimulus showed a strong spontaneous preference and high constancy to blue, revealing a robust short-wavelength bias. Crucially, the strength of this spontaneous bias depended on reward concentration; Low-reward conditions elicited strong blue constancy, whereas high-reward conditions weakened it, demonstrating that reward expectation shapes spontaneous colour choices. This bias was flexible. When bees learned that yellow was rewarding, they switched their preferences. Bees sequentially trained to both colours visited blue and yellow, showing no overall bias, or effect of the last-trained colour, indicating that recent experiences disrupt colour-specific constancy and generate largely random foraging choices. Bees were capable of learning and retaining two colours simultaneously, effectively suppressing the influence of spontaneous preferences. Finally, analysis of the community floral spectral distribution revealed a strong dominance of short-wavelength flowers, suggesting that long-term selection by the local floral environment may underlie the spontaneous blue preference observed in A. dorsata.</description>
  <category>animal behavior and cognition</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>EEG-Based Decoding of Color and Visual Category Representations Is Reliable Within and Across Sessions</title>
  <dc:creator>Frenkel, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Deouell, L. Y.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The human visual system represents stimuli in a rich and detailed manner. Traditional methods of studying visual representations in humans, such as event-related potentials (ERP), revealed numerous distinctions between the brain activity elicited by different categories of stimuli. However, these methods miss the information embedded in the spatial distributions of brain activity, or patterns, and are not always sensitive to study visual representations of different stimuli at the single participant or single trial level. Time-resolved multivariate pattern classification analysis (MVPA), or Decoding, efficiently extracts the visual representations of stimuli from the EEG topography without a-priori assumptions about the location of the effect in time and space at the single participant level. The rich information this method provides has increased its popularity dramatically in recent years. Yet, different participants show variable quality of decoding performance, and it is unclear if the accuracy of decoding is maintained within participants across multiple sessions, tasks, attentional conditions and visual features. In the current study, participants performed three visual tasks, over two sessions (1-7 days apart). We examined the correlation of decoding accuracy: within the cross-validation set, between sessions, between features (color and category) and to different measurements of the ERP signal and behavioral performance. We also examined how models generalized to different tasks and different attention conditions. We found that decoding accuracies varied substantially across participants, and that decoding accuracy was reliable within participant, over sessions, attention condition and task. This suggests the decodability behaves like an individual trait. Moreover, the spatial patterns underlying the decoding (classification weights) generalized across different tasks, attentional conditions and sessions. This suggests minimal representational drift at the resolution allowed by the EEG. We conclude that EEG decoding is a reliable method, and that visual representations are stable.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An Adenine-Based Molecular Rotor as a Universal Fluorescent Nucleobase with High Brightness</title>
  <dc:creator>Pushkarevskaya, A. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kamzeeva, P. N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Belyaev, E. S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Brylev, V. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lomzov, A. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Aralov, A. V.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Chemically modified nucleic acids have become a powerful platform for basic research and applied technologies. Universal nucleobases are used in PCR,sequencing, and the design of nanodevices and aptamers. Fluorescent universal nucleobases have an even wider range of applications, including the development of nucleic acid-based sensors, switches, and relay logic gates. However, few such nucleobases have been proposed to date, and most of them have suboptimal optical properties. Here, we propose an adenine-based molecular rotor, 7,8-dihydro-8-oxo-6-(3-methylbenzo[d]thiazol-2(3H)-ylidene)adenine (oxo-AdeBZT), as a new, remarkably bright and potent fluorescent universal nucleobase. Its brightness in both oligodeoxyribonucleotides (ODNs) and DNA duplexes (4200 - 10000 M-1 * cm-1) originates from a high molar extinction coefficient (averaged 37000 M-1 * cm-1), provided by the appended 3-methylbenzo[d]thiazolyl moiety, and a relatively high quantum yield (0.11 - 0.27). Melting temperature variations observed upon the incorporation of oxo-AdeBZT opposite native nucleobases in a duplex context did not exceed 10%. The basis of these universal hybridizing properties was unveiled using computational methods. According to molecular dynamics simulations, oxo-AdeBZT pushes the opposite nucleobase out of the DNA double helix and forms multiple hydrophobic contacts with the flanking base pairs. At the same time, the rotational mobility of the bonds between the oxo-AdeBZT-constituting heterobicycles decreases, and oxo-AdeBZT adopts a planar conformation in both ODNs and their duplexes, resulting in the light-up effect. These properties make oxo-AdeBZT a promising molecular tool for analytical, biophysical and biochemical studies.</description>
  <category>biophysics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Behavior evolves as a correlated response to selection on cuticle color in Drosophila melanogaster and D. simulans</title>
  <dc:creator>Ruckman, S. N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Duffy, A. G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mendez, P. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>McCaffery, K. D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Miller, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Crews, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tan, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Campbell, L. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>March, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Brown, E. B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Houle, D.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Understanding whether traits evolve independently or as integrated units is central to predicting adaptive evolution. Correlated trait evolution can reflect genetic covariation, such that selection on one trait can constrain or redirect evolutionary responses in others. Here, we used artificial selection on cuticle color in Drosophila melanogaster and D. simulans to investigate whether color and behavior evolve in tandem. We selected for light and dark thoracic colors across 16 generations in two populations per species and measured correlated responses in a suite of behavioral traits, including aggression, basal activity, total activity, sleep, and geotaxis. Dark selected individuals generally showed higher aggression and basal activity than light selected or control flies across both species and sexes, pointing to a modest but repeatable correlated response that must be interpreted in light of low and variable aggression in our assay. In contrast, patterns for geotaxis, sleep, and total activity evolved unpredictably, often varying across species and populations, and showed no clear or uniform association with color. Taken together, our results suggest that some behaviors may share a predictable relationship with color, whereas others behave largely independently under the conditions we examined. The persistence of correlated responses in aggression and basal activity in response to selection on color is consistent with a conserved genetic basis, such as pleiotropy or tight linkage, although our data do not, by themselves, distinguish among these mechanisms. Future work that identifies the loci underlying variation in both color and behavior and tests their effects experimentally will be important for clarifying how multivariate genetic covariance shapes the direction and pace of adaptive evolution.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Differential effectiveness of bee and beetle pollinators creates flower colour polymorphism</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinze, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>van der Kooi, C. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Spaethe, J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Floral diversity is the hallmark of Angiosperms and is often shaped by pollinator-mediated selection, which drives floral divergence as plants evolve traits that attract specific pollinator groups. Mediterranean red, bowl-shaped flowers are specialized on pollination by glaphyrid beetles in areas with beetles and bees but evolved different colours and specialize on bees as pollinators when beetles are absent. What explains this geographic variation in specialization and concomitant flower colour differences? We assessed pollination effectiveness of honeybees and glaphyrids for the colour-polymorphic Anemone pavonina in its natural habitat. We recorded the duration and number of flower visits and quantified single-visit seed set. Per-visit effectiveness (relative seed set) was threefold higher for Pygopleurus (36.3%) than for honeybees (9.5%). Flower visitation lasted substantially longer for beetles (56.3 sec. on average) than for honeybees (2.3 sec.). For beetles, pollinator importance (single-visit seed set x visitation frequency) was highest at low elevations but declined with increasing elevation, whereas for bees pollinator importance remained low yet constant across the elevational gradient. The high pollinator effectiveness of beetles indicates that floral specialization for this pollinator group is advantageous, even to the point that excluding low-quality bee pollinators - by producing inconspicuous flower colours - is beneficial. Non-red flowers may only be beneficial at higher elevations, where bee pollinator importance exceeds that of beetles.</description>
  <category>animal behavior and cognition</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The cuticle lamellae responsible for structural coloration in red algae display common features with the metazoan extracellular matrix</title>
  <dc:creator>Philippe, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Godfroy, O.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Beisson, F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gautier, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jouanneau, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Le Panse, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Com, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Delage, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Czjzek, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ficko-Blean, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Collen, J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Structural coloration is a physical phenomenon observed in many living organisms, including seaweeds, via the formation of highly organized nanostructures. Although a widespread system is characterized by the deposition of multilayer thin-film in the extracellular matrix (ECM), enabling light interference, to date such lamellae have only been described in the cuticle of red algae belonging to the Gigartinaceae family within macroalgae. Here, we determine the composition of the multilayered cuticle components in the model species Chondrus crispus (Rhodophyta), using genomic, transcriptomic, proteomic, metabolomic and analytical profiling of carbohydrates. The complex structural assembly revealed common features with the ECM of animals. The carbohydrate fraction consists of a complex mixture of ECM carrageenans and glycosaminoglycan-like structures. A major von Willerbrand factor A domain (VWA) protein plays a critical role for the adhesion of macromolecules, including protein-protein interactions and to sulfated polysaccharides. We propose the name of Lamellae Cohesive Protein (LCP) regarding the alternate distribution of chemically distinct constituents within the cuticle. For the first time, we identified major proteins of the algal cuticle, providing a framework for addressing the evolutionary origins of the algal cuticle biosynthesis and raise important questions regarding its role, particularly across the life cycle marked by major structural ECM modifications.</description>
  <category>biochemistry</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lysosome-Related Organelles Orchestrate Guanine Crystal Formation in Pigment Cells</title>
  <dc:creator>Gorelick-Ashkenazi, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Barzilay, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lerer-Goldshtein, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Olender, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Eyal, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Glaser, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Broder, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mishol, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Deis, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kedmi, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gur, D.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Iridosomes, the guanine crystal-forming organelles of pigment-producing iridophores, are among the most versatile, visually striking yet mechanistically uncharacterized organelles in vertebrate biology. Lysosome-related organelles (LROs) support cell type-specific functions by adapting endolysosomal pathways for specialized roles. Here, we show that iridosomes represent a previously unrecognized subtype of LROs. Using transcriptomic profiling of zebrafish iridophores, CRISPR-Cas9-mediated gene disruption, and cryogenic transmission electron microscopy, we define the molecular program underlying iridosome biogenesis. Iridosomes have evolved unique adaptations for crystal growth while retaining core features of other LROs. Key regulators, including RAB32a, AP3M2, and HPS5, are essential for crystal formation, with gene knockouts causing reduced crystal number, altered morphology, and distinct maturation defects. We further identify hallmark LRO features in iridosomes, including intraluminal vesicles and pH-regulated developmental transitions. Cross-species transcriptomic analysis confirms that iridosomes share an LRO signature across vertebrates, including teleost fish and reptiles, suggesting ancient evolutionary origins. These findings establish iridosomes as crystalline LROs and as a model for investigating how cells construct structurally specialized organelles through coordinated trafficking, acid-base regulation, and crystallization, with implications for LRO evolution and human disease.</description>
  <category>developmental biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Environmental Variation Promotes Convergent Evolution and Rapid Diversification of Wing Shape and Color in Skipper Butterflies</title>
  <dc:creator>Matos-Maravi, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Linke, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ribeiro, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lamas, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Freitas, A. V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nunez, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kawahara, A. Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Toussaint, E. F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bacon, C. D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wahlberg, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Antonelli, A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Predation is a key driver of speciation and phenotypic diversification, yet how antipredator traits evolve and persist over evolutionary time remains poorly understood. We generated target sequence capture and whole-genome sequencing data for the skipper butterfly subfamily Eudaminae (Hesperiidae) to test whether antipredator defenses, in interaction with environmental variation, promote diversification. We focus on two antipredation wing traits: hindwing tails, which deflect predator attacks, and blue-green coloration, which may enhance motion dazzle and be used as warning coloration. Applying phylogenomics, morphometrics, and comparative methods, we model trait evolution in relation to diel activity and geographic distribution and find that hindwing tails repeatedly evolved at least seven times and blue-green coloration at least fifteen times. Both traits are associated with elevated speciation rates, but evolutionary transitions toward tailless wings and non-iridescent coloration occurred more frequently than trait gains, indicating high evolutionary lability of these antipredator defenses. Trait loss, particularly pronounced in tropical diurnal species, may reflect trade-offs in flight performance, shifts in predation guilds, or the evolution of alternative defensive traits. Our findings highlight rampant convergent evolution of wing traits that are under strong predator-mediated selection. By identifying how antipredator defenses and environmental contexts influence phenotypic and species diversification, this study provides new insights into the ecological and evolutionary processes underlying insect diversity.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
