<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ColSci publications &amp; preprints</title>
<link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
<atom:link href="https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.16</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A common mechanism and multiple advantages of pigment loss underlie the convergent evolution of albinism in cave animals</title>
  <dc:creator>Bilandzija, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Renner, K. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cetkovic, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jeffery, W. R.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The loss of pigmentation is a hallmark adaptation of cave-dwelling animals but the underlying mechanisms are poorly understood. This study investigates the cellular and biochemical basis of albinism, the loss of melanin pigment, which convergently evolved across a wide range of cave animals. Is albinism caused by the interruption of pigment synthesis or elimination of the pigment cell lineage? The results suggest that albinism evolved by a common mechanism, a block in the first step of the melanin biosynthesis pathway, the conversion of L-tyrosine to L-DOPA, in diverse albino cave animals ranging from annelids and mollusks to vertebrates. Pigment cells are conserved in all tested albino cave species and distributed in patterns resembling pigmentation in their close surface relatives. The cells capable of melanin synthesis when provided with L-DOPA substrate were detected at the sites of injuries in a cave annelid, cave mollusk, and cave teleost, suggesting roles in innate immunity during tissue repair, which may explain why pigment cells are conserved despite the loss of pigment production. Next, we focused on the longstanding issue of the evolutionary forces involved in the regression of pigmentation in cave animals and explored hypotheses of why losing pigmentation might be adaptive in cave environments. First, we tested the hypothesis that pigment regression may conserve energy, which is important for survival in the food-limited cave environment. Our results indicate that melanin synthesis has a marked energetic cost in the cavefish, Astyanax mexicanus. Lastly, we show that the disruption of melanin synthesis at its first biosynthetic step is correlated with increased dopamine levels in multiple depigmented cavefish populations, including populations that evolved albinism independently. This result supports a widespread tradeoff between the melanin and catecholamine synthesis pathways in A. mexicanus. We conclude that the interruption of the conversion of L-tyrosine to L-DOPA in the synthesis of melanin confers multiple advantages that could serve as targets of natural selection, supporting an adaptive hypothesis for the evolution of albinism in cave animals.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Generalizability of machine learning models for plant traits using hyperspectral reflectance data: The case of maize</title>
  <dc:creator>Xu, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ferguson, J. N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kromdijk, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nikoloski, Z.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Hyperspectral reflectance provides rapid and precise phenotyping of plants in a non-destructive manner both in field and well-controlled settings. The resulting data have been used to devise machine learning (ML) models for paired measurements of different traits in diverse plants and crops. Yet, despite advances in using of hyperspectral data to reliably predict crop traits of interest, there are pressing issues concerning the training of ML models, the aggregation of data from crop field trials, and the generalizability of the models in different prediction settings. We collected hyperspectral reflectance data along with 25 anatomical, gas exchange, and chlorophyll fluorescence traits from 320 recombinant inbred lines of a maize Multi-Parent Advanced Generation Inter-Cross population grown across three consecutive seasons. We use these data to systematically: (1) compare the performance of representative ML models for different traits, including slow fluorescence kinetics whose predictability by hyperspectral data has not yet been investigated, (2) evaluate the ML model performance in prediction scenarios concerning unseen genotypes, unseen seasons, and the combination thereof, (3) investigate the effects of data aggregation of ML model performance. These problems are addressed in a rigorous nested cross-validation setting that provides a template for adequate assessment of performance of ML models for diverse crop traits considering the particularities of the experimental design.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Purification and pigment analysis of diadinoxanthin-binding PSI-LHCI supercomplexes from Euglena gracilis strain Z</title>
  <dc:creator>Sakamoto, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kato, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nakajima, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shen, J.-R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nagao, R.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Euglena gracilis, a phototrophic flagellate, possesses light-harvesting complexes (LHCs) with a pigment composition distinct from that of land plants and green algae, despite notable similarities in LHC polypeptide sequences to green algae. Here, we purified photosystem I-LHCI (PSI-LHCI) supercomplexes from E. gracilis strain Z and characterized their biochemical and spectroscopic properties. The purified complex exhibited a unique pigment profile, notably including diadinoxanthin that is typically found in red-lineage organisms, setting E. gracilis apart from green-lineage organisms. The absorption spectrum displayed the Qy band of chlorophyll a at 675nm, while the 77-K fluorescence-emission spectrum revealed a prominent peak at 732nm, closely resembling those in land plants. These features suggest that long-wavelength chlorophylls bound to LHCI may be evolutionarily conserved. Nevertheless, the absence of neoxanthin, lutein, and violaxanthin further differentiates the Euglena LHCIs from other oxyphototrophs. Together, these results illuminate the evolutionary diversification of PSI-LHCI supercomplexes and offer insights into the unique pigment-binding features of the Euglena light-harvesting system.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Association of iridescence and tails with flight proxies suggests that predation drives convergence in skipper butterflies</title>
  <dc:creator>Linke, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Debat, V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Matos-Maravi, P.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Phenotypic evolution is shaped by phylogenetic, ecological and biomechanical constraints. Butterfly wings offer an ideal system to explore these constraints as their evolution is strongly influenced by natural and sexual selection affecting colour patterns and wing shape in relation to visual signalling and flight performance. We focus on Eudamina skippers, butterflies with large-scale phenotypic convergences involving wing shape and colour pattern. Using a comprehensive morphometric dataset encompassing 176 species, we assess their morphological evolution in a phylogenetic framework. We show that hindwing tails and dorsal iridescence, proposed to signal high escape ability, have repeatedly evolved in tropical species. Hindwing tails are associated with intermediate body size, low wing loading and a forewing shape that facilitates manoeuvrability; iridescence is more common in large species with significantly high wing loading and aspect ratio, indicating high flight speed and manoeuvrability. The evolution of all tested morphometric traits is best described by Ornstein-Uhlenbeck models, indicating stabilising selection around fitness optima in Eudamina. Models testing for random drift or early burst dynamics were rejected in all cases. We reveal a clear co-evolution between the fore- and hindwing shapes, despite both wings having different functional constraints. Hindwing tails have a significant recurrent effect on forewing shape in lineages evolving them independently, suggesting the existence of evolutionary trade-offs between flight performance and antipredator defences. Our study shows that the convergent morphologies across Eudamina have likely arisen not by neutral evolution but by ecological selection influenced by biomechanical constraints.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Monitoring Forest Foliar Moisture Using Sentinel-2 Reflectance and Radiative Transfer Model Inversion</title>
  <dc:creator>Kotzur, I.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Boer, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yebra, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Moore, B. D.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Foliar moisture content (FMC) of forests canopies is important for understanding biodiversity, including animal habitat quality for forest-dependent fauna and forest fire risk. In this study, we modelled spatiotemporal variation in FMC using optical remote sensing. We inverted the PROSPECT and GEOSAIL Radiative Transfer Models (RTM) on Sentinel-2 satellite reflectance data of 20 m ground resolution to retrieve FMC, and then predicted FMC at sub-continental scales using a random forest (RF) regression emulation of the RTM model. An RTM look-up-table, from earlier work, was filtered by ecological criteria from 24 sites sampled along precipitation and canopy cover gradients and was inverted by using the spectral angle, as a merit function. The RF emulator allowed efficient computation and presentation of an extensive and fine-scale forest FMC data cube of interest in animal, fire and plant ecology. Our RTM-based, predictions of forest and woodland FMC had a root mean square error (RMSE) of 19.9% of dry matter content and explained more than 60% of variance (r2 = 0.62). This represents an improvement over previous models using reflectance data of coarser spatial resolution, particularly in terms of explained variance (r2=0.17 and RMSE=32%). The emulator model achieved similar performance to the RTM with slightly larger error (RMSE = 21.77%) and smaller explained variance (r2 = 0.54). Overall, both models performed best in forests, and woodlands of moderate to high canopy density (&gt; ~0.75 LAI). This study demonstrates that FMC can be monitored at spatial resolutions that allow intra- or inter-landscape patterns to be resolved surpassing previous capabilities.</description>
  <category>ecology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bird species with color polymorphism have greater ecological success</title>
  <dc:creator>Kazuya, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sato, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sekercioglu, C. H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Noriyuki, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Takahashi, Y.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The explanation of the variation in ecological success of species is one of the key challenges in ecology, evolutionary biology and conservation biology. Here, we discuss the function of polymorphism in body color which is one of the most conspicuous features of organisms strongly affecting the performance of species. We applied a phylogenetic comparative approach to assess whether body color polymorphisms contribute to species success in birds, reflected in distributional ranges, extinction risk, and current population trends. We compiled and analyzed a comprehensive global dataset that included the distribution, phylogeny, ecology and morphological traits of all extant bird species. Species with body color polymorphism showed larger distributional ranges, larger environmental ranges, lower risk of extinction, and more stable population trends. Our analyses suggest that the presence of color polymorphism contributes to avian species success at the global scale, especially reflected in lower extinction likelihood and better population trends.</description>
  <category>ecology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hawkmoths learn best without negative reinforcement in a differential colour association task</title>
  <dc:creator>Manel, A. N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Foster, J. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Stöckl, A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Visual learning in insects can be strongly influenced by the underlying context and conditions. Improved colour learning has been demonstrated using differential conditioning with reward-aversion paradigms in insects like wasps, bumblebees, and honeybees, where substances that induce strong aversion, such as quinine, enable more accurate discrimination. Although learning outcomes of differential conditioning are closely tied to the perceived reward and aversion, few studies have compared the role of negative reinforcements in shaping associations, and their relevance across insect groups. In our study, we compare the role of aversive substances for differential in the hummingbird hawkmoth, Macroglossum stellatarum, a diurnal moth that relies on vision for foraging. Tying to previous learning studies in insects, we paired a sugar-rewarded target with a distractor that was paired with either quinine, salt, citric acid, water, or was presented with no aversive substance. Learning outcomes were compared by inverting a strong colour preference between perceptually close or distant colour pairs, to provide tasks with disparate challenges. Contrary to results from other insect species, we found that moths trained with quinine were worse at switching preferences between similar colours compared to training with citric acid and appetitive-only differential conditioning. We also show that quinine interferes with sucrose perception, potentially impairing target acquisition during training. Additionally, we link differences in learning arising from the negative reinforcements to their impact on exploration during foraging. Our results highlight the role of experience in modulating behaviour and discuss the importance of interpreting learning outcomes based on an animal&#39;s sensory ecology and foraging dynamics.</description>
  <category>animal behavior and cognition</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mechanism of PMC (2,2,5,7,8-pentamethyl-6-chromanol), a sterically hindered phenol antioxidant, in rescuing oxidized low-density lipoprotein-induced cytotoxicity in human retinal pigment epithelial cells</title>
  <dc:creator>Chaudhary, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Moon, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hu, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kriukov, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pestun, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baranov, P. Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ng, Y.-S. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Damore, P. A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Geographic atrophy or late stage dry age-related macular degeneration (AMD) is characterized by drusen deposition and progressive retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) degeneration, leading to irreversible vision loss. The formation of drusen leads to dyshomeostasis, oxidative stress and irreversible damage to RPE. In this study, we used an in vitro model of oxidized-low density lipoproteins (ox-LDL) induced human RPE damage/death model to investigate the mechanism whereby a sterically hindered phenol antioxidant compound, PMC (2,2,5,7,8-pentamethyl-6-chromanol) protects RPE against ox-LDL-induced damage. We show that PMC exerts its protective effect by preventing the upregulation of stress-responsive heme oxygenase-1 (HMOX1/HO-1) and NAD(P)H:quinone oxidoreductase (NQO1) at mRNA and protein levels. This effect was due to PMC mediated blockade of ROS generation, which in turn blocked nuclear translocation of the Nuclear factor erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2) transcription factor, ultimately preventing the upregulation of antioxidant response elements (ARE), including HMOX1 and NQO1. A key role for HO-1 was demonstrated when the protective effect of PMC was inhibited by the knockdown of HMOX1. Additionally, treatment of PMC under different experimental conditions and time points revealed that the continuous presence of PMC is required for optimal protection against ox-LDL-induced cytotoxicity, defining the cellular pharmacokinetics of the molecule. Our data demonstrate the involvement of a key antioxidant pathway through which PMC mitigates oxidative stress induced by ox-LDL and provides a potential therapeutic strategy to suppress RPE degeneration/damage during AMD progression.</description>
  <category>molecular biology</category>
  <category>confirmatory results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sustained Lysosomal Delivery of Enhanced Cy3-Labeled Acid Nanoparticles Restores Lysosomal pH in Retinal Pigment Epithelial Cells and Astrocytes</title>
  <dc:creator>Li, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wang, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lu, W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jishkariani, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tsourkas, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kaja, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nair, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dunaief, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mitchell, C. H.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Lysosomal pH is frequently elevated in age-dependent neurodegenerations like Age-related Macular Degeneration (AMD), Alzheimer&#39;s Disease (AD), and Parkinson&#39;s Disease (PD). Tools that restore lysosomal pH to an optimal acidic range could enhance enzymatic degradation and reduce waste accumulation. Acidic nanoparticles offer a promising strategy for restoring lysosomal function, but accurate tracking of organelle delivery and long-term retention is needed to optimize dosage. To improve detection and enhance delivery, nanoparticles were synthesized from Poly(D,L-lactide-co-glycolide) (PLGA) polymers covalently linked to the fluorescent Cyanine3 amine (Cy3) probe. Nanoparticle concentration and loading times were optimized to achieve &gt;90% delivery to lysosomes in cultured induced pluripotent stem cell-derived retinal pigment epithelial (iPS-RPE) cells. Uptake was heterogeneous, varying between adjacent cells. Once loaded into lysosomes, the nanoparticles were stably retained, with no detectable changes in concentration, distribution, or size for at least 28 days. iPS-RPE cells internalized more nanoparticles than the ARPE-19 cell line or mouse optic nerve head astrocyte cultures. Functionally, PLGA nanoparticles restored an acidic pH and cathepsin D levels in compromised lysosomes. In summary, Cy3-PLGA nanoparticles enabled improved tracking and long-term delivery to lysosomes, supporting future in vivo applications to restore lysosomal pH in aging and degenerating tissues.</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>ttc39bl, one of the two duplicated paralogs of the tetratricopeptide repeat domain 39B gene, is essential for carotenoid coloration in medaka (Oryzias latipes) and is the gene responsible for the r locus.</title>
  <dc:creator>Kimura, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Inoue, I.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Body color plays key roles in fitness, communication with others, and hiding. In poikilothermal vertebrates, the body color is mainly determined by types and distributions of chromatophores. Among them, carotenoid color of xanthophores/erythrophores is important for interspecific diversity and colorful males as sexual dimorphism. Most vertebrates cannot synthesize carotenoids in their bodies and must ingest them from food. However, the genes involved in the uptake process are not fully understood. Therefore, we tried to identify the causal gene of the carotenoid color mutant of medaka. The HdrR-II1 strain used in the genome project has orange body color in males and white body color in females. The orange and white body color was known to be controlled by the sex-linked R locus, but the causal gene of this was unknown. In this study, we identified that the causal gene of the R locus is tetratricopeptide repeat domain 39b like (ttc39bl). In the HdrR-II1, the ttc39bl on the Y chromosome is normal, but the ttc39bl on the X chromosome has an 821 bases insertion in exon 3 and is broken. This insertion is also present on both the X and Y chromosomes of commercially available white medaka.</description>
  <category>zoology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Quantifying Misuse of Color in Biological Research</title>
  <dc:creator>Lin, T.-J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hillman, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kim, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Garg, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Duong, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Landry, M. P.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Colors are widely used to report biological research data. Effective interpretation of colors relies on accurate, intuitive, and accessible colormaps that are properly labeled. Misuse of colormaps, such as using rainbow, mismatched, and other inaccessible colormaps, hinders reader interpretation. Despite their ubiquitous use to represent biological data, the prevalence of colormap misuse has not been quantified. Using established guidelines, we analyzed over 6,000 articles in 10 high-impact biological journals spanning 2020-2024 to quantify the prevalence of colormap use and misuse. Over 67% of articles contain at least one colormap, of which 81% contain some form of misuse. Among the over 11,000 acquired colormap-associated figures, 60% contain some form of misuse. Heatmaps, scatter plots, images, and image overlays are the most commonly used figures with colormaps. These statistics vary by journal but remain constant over time, demonstrating the urgent need to increase awareness and education about color-based data reporting guidelines.</description>
  <category>scientific communication and education</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Take it or leaf it: bees learn leaf shape as a cue when flower color is easily learned</title>
  <dc:creator>Castagna, A. M. T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Burrow, J. K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Stewart, C. G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Russell, A. L.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Over a century of research has demonstrated that pollinators, such as bees, associatively learn diverse flower cues, including tactile, visual, and olfactory cues, to find food rewards. However, floral cues are not always reliable, as flowers of different plant species often differ in terms of the qualities of their food rewards, even when flower types resemble each other. At the same time, some non-floral traits, such as leaf shape, differ reliably among plant species and might be associatively learned by bees to improve foraging success. In this laboratory study, we tested whether generalist bees (Bombus impatiens) can (1) associatively learn differences in leaf shape to discriminate rewarding from unrewarding flowers and (2) rely more on differences in leaf shape when a flower color cue is harder to discriminate. We therefore assigned bees to either of two treatments: in one treatment, rewarding and unrewarding artificial targets (&quot;flowers&quot;) differed greatly in petal color, and in the other treatment, they differed little; each treatment&#39;s targets differed in leaf shape in the same way. As expected, bees learned significantly faster when flower petal colors were more dissimilar and thus relatively easier to discriminate. These bees also learned and recalled the correct combination of petal color and leaf shape. Yet when petal colors differed relatively little, bees had a much harder time learning petal color and did not show evidence of having remembered leaf shape. Our results demonstrate that leaf shape is a cue that foraging bees can learn to associate with a pollen food reward. However, leaf shape may be learned secondarily to, or only in combination with floral cues (such as petal color). We discuss evidence of compound learning and overshadowing and implications of our results for pollinator-mediated selection on non-floral plant traits.</description>
  <category>animal behavior and cognition</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pupil size correlates with near-threshold detection performance irrespective of stimulus colour, eccentricity, or retinal adaptation-state</title>
  <dc:creator>Ruuskanen, V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mathot, S.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>In near-threshold detection tasks, larger pre-stimulus pupil size is associated with improved accuracy. However, previous studies have used black and white peripherally presented stimuli, leaving open the question of whether the relationship persists when targets differ in their colour or eccentricity. Across three experiments (in years 2022-2024), we tested a total of 124 participants while systematically varying the lighting conditions and target properties in a near-threshold detection task. Light conditions ranged from dark to dim to bright, with the dark condition including a period of dark-adaptation. Possible target colours were blue and red on a black background (dark condition), blue and red on a grey background (dim condition), or yellow and cyan on a white background (bright condition). Possible target eccentricities ranged from parafoveal to peripheral, in a continuous manner (experiment 3) or as two predefined near and far eccentricities (experiments 1 &amp; 2). Across all experiments we show that larger pre-stimulus pupil size is associated with improved performance. This large-pupil advantage is not modulated by the colour or eccentricity of the targets, the illumination of the testing room, or retinal adaptation-state. We conclude that the phenomenon is robust, indicating that pupil size affects vision in a behaviourally relevant manner, regardless of the exact conditions.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Redesigning petal shape, size, and color in soybean reveals unexpected phenotypes for floral organ development</title>
  <dc:creator>Szeluga, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>AlBader, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pelletier, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Weis, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Johnson, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fahlgren, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Neequaye, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Vogt, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>DelPercio, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baldrich, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Byers, K. J. R. P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Meyers, B. C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Frank, M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Soybean (Glycine max) has not yet benefited from large-scale hybrid breeding efforts due to its small, self-fertilizing flowers that are difficult to emasculate and limited attractiveness to pollinators. This study explores targeted floral trait engineering to enhance pollinator attraction, aiming to overcome barriers to soybean hybridization. We generated a high-resolution floral organ expression atlas and H3K4 trimethylation ChIP-Seq dataset to identify candidate genes involved in petal development, nectar sugar content, and petal pigmentation. Using CRISPR-based activation and repression systems, we modified the expression of AINTEGUMENTA (GmANT), BIGPETAL (GmBPE), and SUCROSE TRANSPORTER2 (GmSUC2). Contrary to expectations based on Arabidopsis homologs, transcriptional activation of GmANT_B and repression of GmBPE led to reduced, rather than increased, petal size, highlighting divergent regulatory mechanisms in soybean. Complementation of the W1 gene that controls petal pigmentation successfully converted white petals to purple, with preliminary evidence indicating that this color conversion may increase pollinator visitation. These results underscore the complexity of floral development in soybean and provide foundational tools and resources for future efforts to engineer reproductive traits for hybrid seed production.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The role of secondary pollinators in the evolution of complex colour signals in a bimodal pollination system</title>
  <dc:creator>Khoury, K. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Agren, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Peter, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sletvold, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Newman, E. L.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Flower colour is recognized as a key trait influencing pollinator visitation and behaviour, evolved to match the sensory system of a particular pollinator group. However, some flowers combine colours associated with different pollinators, suggesting bimodal adaptation. The perennial herb Cyrtanthus obliquus produces red corollas with yellow tips and is pollinated by birds, but also by bees. To assess the role of the two pollinator categories in shaping selection on the bi-coloured corollas, we examined bee choices in arrays in which the colour signals of plants had been manipulated, and we quantified total as well as bird-mediated phenotypic selection on flower colour using both bird and bee visual models. Bees preferred flowers with a yellow signal over all-red flowers. The analysis of phenotypic selection indicated that both birds and bees influence net selection on flower colour, resulting in conflicting selection on the colour contrast between corolla and corolla tip. Our findings show that the optimal phenotype should depend on the relative importance of the two categories of pollinators in a given population, and are consistent with bimodal adaptation. This study fills an important gap by showing that secondary pollinators can contribute to selection on complex colour signals in angiosperm flowers.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Standardized Method for Insect Color Analyses using Open Source Software: AInsectID Version 1.1 Color Merge</title>
  <dc:creator>Sadia, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Muttaqin, S. S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Alam, P.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The accurate representation of color is important in applications involving species identification. Environmental variations introduce inconsistencies in color perception, affecting the reliability of automated image processing algorithms. In previous work, we developed a hybrid algorithm, AInsectID Version 1.1 Color Merge, to overcome challenges posed by over-segmentation and under-segmentation in insect wing color clustering. We achieved this by using color differences between superpixels to measure homogeneity during the superpixels segmentation process. Nevertheless, our algorithm remains sensitive to environmental effects, affecting its performance and accuracy in color analyses. Here, we introduce a standard imaging method for insect species, as a pre-requisite to analysis in AInsectID Version 1.1 Color Merge. We systematically examine the effects of varying lighting conditions, angle of observation, and working distance in a controlled environment to assess their impact on the performance of the algorithm. We find that by meticulously controlling lighting, working distance, and lighting angle, we develop an evidence-based standard approach to imaging colors that is robust and repeatable. By following our standardized procedure, consistent color analyses are possible under varying environmental conditions. The method was tested using the Delta E2000 ({Delta}E) color difference metric with a threshold of 1, demonstrating that our standard approach maintains perceptual accuracy within the Just Noticeable Difference (JND) range, while improving the reliability of color analyses of insect wings in diverse environments. Finally, to validate the robustness of our standardization method, we evaluated the certainty of our results at different levels of confidence.</description>
  <category>zoology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Movi Color: fast and accurate long-read classification with the move structure</title>
  <dc:creator>Tan, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Majidian, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Langmead, B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zakeri, M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The number of reference genomes is rapidly increasing, thanks to advances in long-read sequencing and assembly. While these collections can improve the sensitivity and specificity of classification methods, this requires highly efficient compressed indexes. K-mer-based approaches like Kraken 2 are efficient but limit the analysis to a fixed k-mer length. This is hard for the user to set ahead of time, and suboptimal settings can harm sensitivity and specificity. Methods that use compressed full-text indexes like SPUMONI2 and Cliffy lift this constraint, but are less efficient than k-mer-based tools. Further, these methods either cannot report a full listing of genomes where a match occurs, or cannot scale to large reference databases. We propose new methods and algorithms that use compressed full-text indexes to enable multi class and taxonomic classification. Unlike past compressed-indexing methods for classification, ours uses the move structure, which is extremely fast thanks to its locality of reference. Our method, called Movi Color, augments the main table of the Movi index. Specifically, Movi Color assigns a &quot;color&quot; to each run of the Burrows-Wheeler Transform according to the subset of genomes from which the run suffixes originated. When the reference is highly repetitive, as is typical when indexing pangenomes or reference databases, only certain colors occur, creating opportunities to compress the index. For species-level classification, Movi Color achieves over 1.6x higher precision and 2x higher recall than Kraken 2 and Metabuli. At the genus level, it achieves 70% higher precision and 80% higher recall. Movi Color&#39;s read processing time is 7-20x faster than Metabuli and is comparable to Kraken 2. Although Movi Color uses more memory than both Kraken 2 and Metabuli,its speed-accuracy trade-off makes it well-suited for real-time or high-throughput scenarios.</description>
  <category>bioinformatics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>High-throughput iNaturalist image analysis reveals flower color divergence in Monarda fistulosa</title>
  <dc:creator>McKenzie, P. F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Church, S. H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hopkins, R.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Characterizing patterns of trait variation across widespread species is a fundamental goal of natural history. Here we create a pipeline to analyze a large community science dataset and test hypothesized flower color divergence across the range of a widespread wildflower. Monarda fistulosa is a North American perennial that produces showy lavender inflorescences. Although previous literature suggests that the flowers of western M. fistulosa might display a deeper purple color than the eastern varieties, this divergence has not been assessed at scale. We process over 40,000 community science photographs of M. fistulosa to identify flowers and extract color. We demonstrate that the flowers of the montane western variety have lower lightness and higher chroma, corresponding to a deeper violet color, than those of eastern M. fistulosa. Our approach and validation provides a scalable framework for phenotyping community science images and enables analysis of geographic color variation in other widespread species.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Spectral Image Scanning Microscope for Multi-Color High-Resolution Imaging</title>
  <dc:creator>Bram, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tal-Friedman, O.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fibeesh, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bar-Sinai, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Flaxer, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Roichman, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ebenstein, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jeffet, J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Fluorescence confocal microscopy is a fundamental and widely used tool for biological, medical, and chemical research. It enables color-coded visualization of sample components, enhancing our understanding of life&#39;s building blocks and their interactions. The recent realization of image scanning microscopy (ISM) using confocal spinning disks (CSD) enhanced the spatial resolution of fluorescence microscopy to twice the diffraction limit with minimal sample perturbation and fast acquisition rates. However, capturing multi-color images using ISM is still time-consuming and introduces temporal artifacts as different colors are not acquired simultaneously. Here, we present a spectral CSD-ISM system designed for concurrent high-resolution and simultaneous multi-color acquisition. By integrating a custom linear Amici prism into the CSD-ISM optical detection path, we achieve multi-color, super-resolution images at a fraction of the acquisition time and with a flexible color palette selection. A digital signal processor (DSP) is employed together with accompanying software as a cost-effective alternative to Field-Programmable Gate Arrays (FPGAs) used in previous studies. We provide an accompanying GPU-compatible, python-based image processing pipeline to decompose spectral signatures into multi-color channel-based images, preserving the optical resolution. System characterization using three color fluorescent beads demonstrated 1.74-fold resolution improvement over the diffraction limit and accurate color classification with three times faster acquisition compared to standard CSD-ISM. Application to neuron cells expressing a Parkinson&#39;s disease-associated mutation, showcased improved resolution and contrast of four distinctly labeled cellular components. This spectral CSD-ISM system provides a valuable tool for biological imaging, enabling the simultaneous acquisition of high-resolution spatial information and multi-color spectral data.</description>
  <category>biophysics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lrrns define a visual circuit underlying brightness and contrast perception</title>
  <dc:creator>Putti, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Faini, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dang, J. T.-M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Eggeler, F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Savaliya, J. H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Duroure, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Vougny, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bahl, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lichtman, J. W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Engert, F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Boulanger-Weill, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Del Bene, F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Albadri, S.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Brightness and contrast are fundamental features of vision, crucial for object detection, environmental navigation, and feeding. Here, we identify a brightness- and contrast-processing circuit in the zebrafish visual system and uncover the role of Leucine-rich repeat neuronal (Lrrn) cell adhesion molecules (CAMs) in regulating its assembly. Deep-projecting retinal ganglion cells (RGCs) serve as the first synaptic relay to the brain requiring Lrrn2 and Lrrn3a for precise axonal targeting and connectivity within the optic tectum. Genetic targeting of these CAMs leads to circuit disorganization and impairments in contrast sensitivity, leading to deficits in visually guided behaviors. Additionally, ultrastructural circuit reconstruction and functional imaging analysis revealed their critical role in luminance processing. These studies define a fundamental visual processing pathway and establish Lrrn CAMs as essential molecular drivers of its assembly.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
