<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ColSci publications &amp; preprints</title>
<link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
<atom:link href="https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.9.8</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Perceiving surface colour requires attention</title>
  <dc:creator>Goddard, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Paul Remician, K.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Colour constancy refers to our ability to distinguish changes in surface properties from changes in the properties of light illuminating the scene. The apparent ease with which we can tell that objects do not change colour, for example, when moving from sunlight to the shade, belies the complexity of solving this ill-constrained problem. Although there is a substantial body of work testing which image cues might be used to accomplish this, there is surprisingly little known of how the brain performs this computation. Here, we tested a fundamental aspect of this perceptual process: whether it requires attention. We measured visual search times for both surface colour (requiring separation of surface and illuminant properties) and &#39;raw&#39;, colorimetric colour (which does not). We found a clear difference between the two: visual search for colorimetric colour was fast and near-parallel, while search for surface colour was slow and consistent with the serial deployment of attention. That is, search times suggest that the perceptual separation of surface and illuminant properties in colour constancy may require an attention-based process analogous to perceiving conjunctions of simple features in &#39;feature binding&#39;. Colour discrimination thresholds suggested that while colorimetric colour detection is fast and parallel, once attention was directed to these stimuli and perceptual scission occurs, colorimetric colour information was discarded by the visual system. These results offer important new insights into the sequence of processes the brain uses to accomplish colour constancy.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Color, size, shape: The drivers of floral variation in Hesperis matronalis (Dames Rocket)</title>
  <dc:creator>Johnson, S. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Rifkin, J. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wright, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baucom, R. S.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Evolutionary biologists have long been intrigued by the factors that sustain genetic and phenotypic variation within and among natural populations. Polymorphisms underlying components of floral display -- such as floral color, size, and shape -- are uniquely of interest since variation in these traits impact pollinator attraction, rates of visitation, and pollinator efficiency, which ultimately influence patterns of plant reproduction and therefore fitness. We leverage existing floral variation present within and among populations of Hesperis matronalis (Dames Rocket) to disentangle the relative influence of natural selection and genetic drift in shaping floral trait variation. We employ a multi-tiered approach: we determine if variation in floral traits (color, size, and petal shape) is influenced by geography or environmental variables such as temperature and precipitation, we evaluate whether selection underlies trait variation by comparing phenotypic divergence (PST) with neutral genetic structure (FST), and we perform a Lande-Arnold selection analysis to explore the relationship between fitness and floral trait variation within natural populations. We find that selection underlies the divergence of floral color, floral size, and petal width among H. matronalis populations, with PST &gt; FST for each trait. We find no indication, however, that variation in size in this species is influenced by the environment, but some evidence that variation in floral color and petal shape may be influenced by temperature. Finally, selection analyses of contemporary populations indicate divergent selection affecting combinations of color, petal shape, and plant size. These results suggest that the variation in floral shape in this species may be maintained due to environmental pressures, whereas floral color is influenced by pollinator visibility and the presence of different pollinator groups.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Effects of color-enhancing filters on color salience in normal trichromats</title>
  <dc:creator>Webster, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Knoblauch, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Simoncelli, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>McPherson, D.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Notch filters can alter color contrasts by selectively filtering different spectral bands of the stimulus and have been developed to enhance reddish-greenish contrasts for color-deficient observers with anomalous trichromacy. We examined the effects of such filters on color salience for normal trichromats, using a visual search paradigm where the task was to locate a color target superimposed on a variegated chromatic background, similar to foraging for fruits among foliage. Background colors varied along a bluish-yellowish or purplish to yellow-green (short-wave cone isolating) axis, roughly spanning the range of dominant color variations in arid or lush environments. Target colors sampled a wide range of hue angles and contrasts. Testing was conducted on a computer monitor, with the filter effects simulated by calculating corresponding chromaticities with or without the filter for naturalistic (Munsell) reflectances. The filter evaluated (Enchroma SuperX glasses) was designed to increase color contrast along a magenta-green axis. Consistent with this, search times for targets on the blue-yellow background were significantly faster for the filter condition, because the filter increased the target-background color difference. Alternatively, overall differences in search times were not observed for the S-cone background. The differences on the two backgrounds could be qualitatively accounted for by the relative salience of the stimuli predicted by a perceptual color space (CIELAB). Our results demonstrate the efficacy of the filters for enhancing visual performance for normal trichromats and naturalistic tasks, and illustrate how these effects depend on the potential color characteristics of the environment.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The hallmark of colour in EEG signal</title>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Our perception of the world is inherently colourful, and colour provides well-documented benefits for vision: it helps us see things quicker and remember them better. We hypothesised that colour is not only central to perception but also a rich and decodable source of information in electroencephalography (EEG) signal recorded non-invasively from the scalp. Previous work has shown that brain activity carries colour information for uniform patches, but it remains unclear whether this extends to natural, complex images where colour is not explicitly cued. To investigate this, we analysed the THINGS EEG dataset, comprising 64-channel recordings from participants viewing 1,800 distinct objects (16,740 images) for 100 ms each, totalling over 82,000 trials. We established a perceptual colour ground truth through a psychophysical experiment in which participants viewed each image for 100 ms and selected perceived colours from a 13-option palette. An artificial neural network trained to predict these scene-level colour distributions directly from EEG signals showed that colour information was robustly decodable (average F-score of 0.5). We next modelled the interaction between colour and object perception in neuroimaging decoding. Images were segmented using the Segment Anything Model (SAM), each object was assigned a representative colour, and features were extracted from these colour-augmented images using CLIP vision encoders. We trained an EEG encoder, CUBE (ColoUr and oBjEct decoding), to align features in both object and colour spaces. Across EEG and MEG datasets in a 200-class recognition task, incorporating colour improved decoding accuracy by about 5%. Together, these findings demonstrate that EEG signal recorded during natural vision carries substantial colour information that interacts with object perception. Modelling this mutual interaction enhances neural decoding performance.</description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Modeling MEK-inhibitor Associated Retinopathy in vitro using human induced-1 pluripotent stem cell-derived retinal pigment epithelial cells</title>
  <dc:creator>Lozano, L. P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jennisch, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jensen, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ratcliff, J. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wiley, L. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Harman, B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Riker, M. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wright, A. T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Erickson, B. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Boldt, H. C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Boyce, T. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mullins, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Binkley, E. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tucker, B. A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Pharmacologic inhibitors of MEK are important anti-cancer drugs but can result in MEK-inhibitor Associated Retinopathy (MEKAR) in which vision is lost due to serous retinal detachments that form via an unknown mechanism. We hypothesized that the cause of this side effect is drug-induced dysfunction of retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) cells. To test this hypothesis, we used human induced pluripotent stem cell-derived RPE cells. We treated mature, hiPSC-derived RPE cells with selumetinib and measured impacts on RPE-specific function, structure, and gene expression. Selumetinib increases the ability of hiPSC-derived RPE to internalize bovine rod outer segments (1.9 vs 3.0, p=0.0024). It also decreases expression of aquaporin 1 during the first 10 days of treatment (2.7 vs 1.1, p=0.0015). It has no effect on the ability of hiPSC-derived RPE to maintain membrane integrity. Selumetinib alters gene expression of hiPSC-derived RPE, with significant changes in genes involved in transport of ions and small molecules regulating cell volume and lysosomal acidification. Selumetinib may lead to subretinal fluid accumulation by both increasing secretions into this space and decreasing outflow.</description>
  <category>molecular biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Aposematic color patterns are the dominant axis of phenotypic diversification in Nymphalid butterflies</title>
  <dc:creator>Luerig, M. D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shirai, L. T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mota, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Willmott, K. R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Freitas, A. V. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Porto, A.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Butterfly wing patterns serve diverse roles in visual communication, from aposematic signaling and mimicry to mate attraction and camouflage. In brush-footed butterflies (Nymphalidae), this diversity can be traced to the wing pattern &quot;ground plan&quot; that generates phenotypes deterministic in origin yet highly multidimensional in form. Quantifying such complexity at scale has long been a challenge, limiting our understanding of how visual signals interact, constrain one another, and evolve. Here, we used computer vision to extract high-dimensional traits from standardized museum specimens and assembled the largest comparative dataset of wing color patterns to date, spanning over one third of all known Nymphalid species. We first tested whether chemically defended species occupy a distinct region in morphospace and then derived a quantitative score for aposematism from the principal color patterns associated with defense. Using this score, we examined whether aposematic signals are expressed consistently across wing surfaces and sexes, and whether their origins are linked to shifts in evolutionary rate. We found that the dominant axis of morphospace is defined by chromatic and achromatic contrast, along which defended and undefended species cluster. Validation with an expert-labeled moth dataset confirmed that this axis separates aposematic from non-aposematic phenotypes across Lepidoptera. Consistent with theory, strongly aposematic species showed greater visual similarity between dorsal and ventral surfaces, between sexes, and among individuals. Rate analyses further indicated that aposematic patterns evolved repeatedly and were associated with non-linear shifts in evolutionary tempo. Together, these results identify aposematism as the dominant organizing axis of wing color pattern evolution in Nymphalidae.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A recurrent sequencing artifact on Illumina sequencers with two-color fluorescent dye chemistry and its impact on somatic variant detection</title>
  <dc:creator>Fu, B. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Viswanadham, V. V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Maziec, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jin, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Park, P. J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The sequencing-by-synthesis technology by Illumina, Inc. enables efficient and scalable readouts of mutations from genomic data. To enhance sequencing speed and efficiency, Illumina has shifted from the four-color base calling chemistry of the HiSeq series to a two-color fluorescent dye chemistry in the NovaSeq series. Benchmarking sequencing artifacts due to biases in the newer chemistry is important to evaluate the quality of identified mutations. We re-analyzed a series of whole-genome sequencing experiments in which the same samples were sequenced on the NovaSeq 6000 (two-color) and HiSeq X10 (four-color) platforms by independent groups. In several samples, we observed a higher frequency of T-to-G and A-to-C substitutions (&quot;T&gt;G&quot;) at the read level for NovaSeq 6000 versus HiSeq X10. As the per-base error rate is still low, the artifactual substitutions have a negligible effect in identifying germline or high variant allele frequency (VAF) somatic mutations. However, such errors can confound the detection of low-VAF somatic variants in high-depth sequencing samples, particularly in studies of mosaic mutations in normal tissues, where variants have low read support and are called without a matched normal. The artifactual T&gt;G variant calls disproportionately occur at NT[TG] trinucleotides, and we leveraged this observation to bioinformatically reduce the T&gt;G excess in somatic mutation callsets. We identified a recurrent artifact specific to the Illumina two-color chemistry platform on the NovaSeq 6000 with the potential to contaminate low-VAF somatic mutation calls. Thus, an unexpected enrichment of T&gt;G mutations in mosaicism studies warrants caution.</description>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Structural basis for color tuning and passive ion conductance in red-shifted pump-fold channelrhodopsin ChR024</title>
  <dc:creator>Takeno, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tajima, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kim, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tsujimura, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ito, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sugiura, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yamashita, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kishi, K. E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fukuda, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nakamura, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Watanabe, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ikeda, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Katayama, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Furutani, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kandori, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ishikita, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Inoue, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kato, H. E.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>ChR024 is a cation-conducting channelrhodopsin with a red-shifted absorption spectrum, recently discovered from a previously unidentified clade through machine-learning-guided gene mining. Due to its unique position in the phylogenetic tree and distinctive spectral properties, it serves as an important model for elucidating rhodopsin evolution and for engineering optogenetic tools with enhanced performance, but its structure and function remain poorly understood. Here, we present cryo-electron microscopy structures of ChR024 in detergent micelles and lipid nanodiscs at resolutions of 3.2 and 2.5 [A], respectively. The structures reveal an architecture strikingly similar to that of ion-pumping rhodopsins, even more so than other pump-like channelrhodopsins such as ChRmine. Structural, theoretical, and spectroscopic analyses uncover a unique color-tuning mechanism, in which charged residues close and distant from the retinal chromophore cooperatively modulate the pKa of the Schiff base counterion and thereby determine the absorption maximum wavelength. Finally, comparative structural analysis of channel- and pump-type rhodopsins, combined with electrophysiology, provides insights into the molecular boundary between these two functional classes and demonstrates the conversion of an outward proton pump into a light-gated channel. Together, these findings illuminate diverse mechanisms of color tuning and functional specification within the rhodopsin family, paving the way for the rational engineering of next-generation optogenetic tools.</description>
  <category>biophysics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Discrimination of Annonaceae using herbarium leaf reflectance spectra under limited sample size conditions</title>
  <dc:creator>Boughalmi, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Santacruz Endara, P. G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bennett, L. A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ecarnot, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bazan, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bastianelli, D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bonnal, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Couvreur, T. L. P.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Herbarium collections offer an unparalleled archive of plant biodiversity, but their use for species identification through spectral data remains constrained by uncertain effects of preservation histories. This study assesses whether a single herbarium specimen can reliably represent its species based on its leaf reflectance spectrum, despite variations in age, geographic origin, or conservation method. We scanned herbarium specimens of different ages and geographic distribution of 14 species of the pantropical Annonaceae. In addition, we used a second dataset of 9 species where some specimens were conserved in alcohol prior to drying and some not. We used five supervised classification models frequently used for high-dimensional data such as spectroscopy. All models achieved high accuracy (&gt;80%) when trained on multiple specimens per species. However, when using only one specimen per species, accuracy varied substantially depending on the taxon. Alcohol preservation prior to drying had little impact on classification success. Our findings demonstrate that herbarium specimens often retain a strong taxonomic signal in their spectra, however, inter-individual variability affects accuracy in some taxa. These findings confirm the usefulness of herbarium spectroscopy as a non-destructive tool for species identification and offer a promising avenue for digitizing historical biodiversity data into high-dimensional trait space.</description>
  <category>plant biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The ecology and adaptive function of clownfish color patterns</title>
  <dc:creator>Froehlich, C. Y. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Caves, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Troscianko, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gibson, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Chiodo, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>De Jode, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Brown, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Luckas, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Titus, B. M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Anti-predator coloration strategies vary widely from conspicuous to cryptic, and everything between. Coloration serves multiple functions, and determining the selective pressures that drive this diversity is a long-standing mystery. Clownfishes display enormous inter- and intra-specific variation in coloration without the influence of sexual selection, providing an excellent system in which to explore these drivers in closely related and sympatric species. Across clownfishes, three color-pattern phenotypes have evolved convergently with host anemone use, implying adaptive functions linked to the host&#39;s physical and chemical properties. Here we conducted a comprehensive study to infer the ultimate functions of clownfish color patterns. By integrating multiple levels of biological organization, including behavior, visual ecology, dietary niche, and microbiome, our data overwhelmingly indicate that specialist and generalist clownfish color patterns have different underlying ecologies and adaptive functions. Specialist clownfishes background match their anemones, remain near hosts, and have specialized diets and microbiomes. Generalists are highly contrasting with their anemones, remain far from hosts, and have variable diets and microbiomes. Taken together, specialist color patterns align with functional expectations of camouflage while generalists align with aposematic or disruptive coloration. Our study provides novel insights into how ecological conditions shape the evolution of multiple anti-predator coloration strategies.</description>
  <category>ecology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Combined multi-color immunofluorescence staining and spatial in situ mRNA expression analysis identifies potential fibrosis drivers in acute lymphoblastic leukemia</title>
  <dc:creator>Braunig, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dencker, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Vo, D. N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fan, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sierras, A. L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Enoksson, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hultquist, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Li, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Scheding, S.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) is the most prevalent childhood cancer. Bone marrow (BM) fibrosis in ALL has been associated with adverse outcomes, however, little is known about the mechanisms that cause fibrosis in ALL. Therefore, we established a novel and advanced analysis method by combining multi-color immunofluorescence staining with in-situ RNA expression analysis (RNAscope) investigate the spatial expression of putative fibrotic drivers in ALL bone marrows. We analyzed standard BM biopsies from pediatric ALL patients. Sequential 5-color immunofluorescence (IF) staining with CD45, CD271, CD31, CD34 and DAPI was used to identify different BM cell types. Combined RNAscope and IF staining was established for spatial mRNA expression analysis of transforming growth factor beta 1 (TGFB1) and platelet-derived growth factor alpha 1 (PDGFA1), which are known to play major roles in primary myelofibrosis (PMF). PMF and normal BM samples served as controls. As expected, ALL bone marrows showed high cellularities and prominent populations of blast cells. CD271+ MSC density was increased in ALL and was associated with fibrosis in a similar manner as observed for PMF. TGFB1 and PDGFA1 expression was considerably increased in ALL megakaryocytes (MKs) compared to PMF patients and normal controls. Furthermore, MK TGFB1 and PDGFA1 expression intensities in fibrotic ALL correlated with fibrosis grade. TGFB1 and PDGFA1 were also expressed in leukemic blasts, however at lower intensities compared to ALL MKs. Taken together, advanced in-situ RNA and IF staining not only revealed increased expression of TGFB1 and PDGFA1 in fibrotic pediatric ALL, but also identified ALL blasts and MKs as their cellular origin at the single cell level. These novel data strongly suggest a role of these cytokines as potential fibrosis drivers in ALL. More broadly, our findings demonstrate that combined RNA and surface marker analysis is a powerful tool to provide new and valuable insights into bone marrow pathophysiology.</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>RPEGENE-Net: A Multi-Resolution Deep Learning Framework for Predicting Gene Expression from Microscopy Images of Retinal Pigment Epithelium (RPE) Cells</title>
  <dc:creator>Nowroozzadeh, M. H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Taghinezhad, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mahmoudi, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sanie-Jahromi, F.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Abstract Purpose: To develop a deep learning framework, RPEGENE-Net, capable of predicting gene expression profiles of retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) cells using live-cell microscopy images. Methods: A dataset of live-cell images of RPE cells, treated with various drug regimens and captured at magnifications of 40x, 100x, 200x, and 400x, was used. Gene expression of six key genes involved in epithelial-mesenchymal transition or EMT (including -SMA, ZEB1, TGF-{beta}, CD90, {beta}-catenin, Snail) and treatment classes (Aflibercept, Bevacizumab, Dexamethasone, Aflibercept + Dexamethasone, and untreated control) were analyzed. After preprocessing the image data and gene expression values, we trained and evaluated twelve state-of-the-art deep learning architectures, including three variants of DenseNet, five variants of ResNet, EfficientNet_b5, Inception_v3, RegNet_y_400mf, and a vision transformer model (Swin_b). A two-stage pipeline was implemented, combining autoencoder-based pretraining to extract meaningful features with fine-tuning specifically optimized for gene expression regression and treatment type classification tasks. Features extracted from the second stage across four magnifications were concatenated to generate the final prediction, leveraging multi-scale morphological information for improved accuracy.</description>
  <category>bioengineering</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sigma-2 Receptor Modulators Alter Low-density Lipoprotein Receptor-mediated Lipid Uptake in Retinal Pigment Epithelial Cells</title>
  <dc:creator>Lizama, B. N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Reaver, A.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Look, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Caggiano, A. O.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hamby, M. E.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Lipid and photoreceptor outer segment (POS) trafficking and digestion are important homeostatic functions of retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) cells, the primary cell type that degenerates in late-stage dry AMD preceded by extracellular drusen deposits of lipids and proteins. The sigma-2 receptor (S2R, TMEM97) interacts with proteins involved in lipid trafficking, such as low-density lipoprotein receptor (LDLR), which is the primary receptor for LDL-cholesterol uptake in the retina. Preclinical studies demonstrate the necessity of S2R in protecting the retina and other nervous system tissues, and loss of either S2R or LDLR has been shown to exacerbate RPE cell death and visual dysfunction. Targeting the regulatory receptors of lipid and protein trafficking functions in RPE cells represents a tractable therapeutic strategy for dry AMD. We previously demonstrated that small molecule modulators of S2R can rescue RPE POS trafficking deficits induced by exogenous stressors. Given that disruption in lipid homeostasis is a key factor in dry AMD pathogenesis and S2R interacts with LDLR, we hypothesized that LDLR-mediated lipid trafficking in RPE could be altered using S2R-targeting small molecules. In this study, RPE cells treated with S2R modulators increased LDL uptake, assessed using fluorescently-labeled LDL, compared to vehicle-treatment. Lentiviral shRNAs to reduce TMEM97 or LDLR expression, or a neutralizing blocking antibody against LDLR, reduced S2R modulator-mediated LDL uptake, confirming the requirement of TMEM97 and LDLR for S2R modulator effects. Together, these data elaborate on a potential mechanism that may underlie the favorable reduction in geographic atrophy lesion size found in participants treated with the S2R modulator zervimensine in the Ph2 clinical trial MAGNIFY in patients with geographic atrophy (COG2201, NCT05893537).</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cell-cell communication as underlying principle governing color pattern formation in fishes</title>
  <dc:creator>Klann, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Miura, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lee, S.-H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Vianello, S. D.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ross, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Watanabe, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gairin, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liang, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hutto, H. W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>McCluskey, B. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Herrera, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Solnica-Krezel, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Besseau, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pigolotti, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Parichy, D. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kinoshita, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Laudet, V.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>The diverse pigmentation patterns of animals are crucial for predation avoidance and behavioral display, yet mechanisms underlying this diversity remain poorly understood. In zebrafish, Turing models have been proposed to explain stripe patterns, but it is unclear if they apply to other fishes. In anemonefish (Amphiprion ocellaris), we identified gja5b, a gene orthologous to zebrafish leopard and encoding a connexin involved in pigment cell communication, as responsible for the Snowflake phenotype. Using CRISPR/Cas9 and transgenesis, we recapitulate the Snowflake phenotype and show expression of gja5b in iridophores. A matching allele was recovered in zebrafish, revealing complementary requirements in both species. Our findings highlight conserved roles of gap junction mediated communication in pigment patterning across divergent teleosts.</description>
  <category>developmental biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Anti-vitronectin single-chain variable fragment targeting the hemopexin-like domain decreases age-related macular degeneration indicators in ex vivo models of the retinal pigment epithelium</title>
  <dc:creator>Kim, J. W.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Meyer, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lopez, B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Faynus, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Johnson, L. V.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hemmati, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Clegg, D. O.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Min, H.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Vitronectin is a prominent constituent of the extracelluar matrix (ECM) that plays a key role in inflammation by regulating cell adhesion, migration, and complement activation. Together with other inflammatory biomarkers, lipids, and hydroxyapatite, an ECM component, vitronectin, accumulates in abnormal deposits and drusen associated with age-related macular degeneration (AMD). Using an engineered polypeptide (VnHX) containing the hexmopexin-like domain (HX) of vitronectin, we found that the HX domain directly promotes hydroxyapatite (HAP) accumulation. Next, we screened humanized single-chain variable fragments (scFvs) against vitronectin that inhibit the interaction between VnHX and HAP, leveraging the binding of VnHX to HAP. We then tested these scFvs for their ability to block Vn-containg deposits secreted by stem cell-derived retinal pigment epithelium (RPE). In this in vitro drusen model, treatment with the anti-vitronectin antibodies decreased vitronectin accumulation. Furthermore, the antibody treatment led to decreased accumulation of C5b-9 and clusterin, indicating alterations in the complement pathway and cellular stress. These results support that vitronectin has a functional role drusen accumulation and possibly in AMD progression. Vitronectin would be a novel, promising therapeutic target for AMD.</description>
  <category>cell biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sex-specific doublesex regulation targeting the color-patterning gene h underlies the evolution of wing sexual dimorphism in the harlequin ladybug Harmonia axyridis</title>
  <dc:creator>Yeki, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kato, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Morita, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shimomura, K.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Niimi, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hinomoto, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Daimon, T.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>ANDO, T.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Organisms on Earth show various forms of sexual dimorphism, including ornaments, weapon traits, and pheromone glands, which has been acquired through sexual selection during evolution. Although the genetic basis of sexual trait has been investigated in diverse species, its evolutionary origin, evolutionary mode, and evolvability remain poorly understood. To address these issues, we investigated the strain-specific sexual dimorphism in elytral color patterns of the harlequin ladybug, Harmonia axyridis, a species with over 200 color morphs. The most basal Red-nSpots type color morph exhibits sexual dimorphism, whereas other derived color morphs have lost it. To investigate how this loss of sexual dimorphism is associated with the emergence of novel color morphs, we investigated the genetic basis of sexual dimorphism by focusing on the master sex differentiation gene, doublesex (dsx). We show that dsx regulates color pattern dimorphism by negatively modulating black spot size in males. This modulation is primarily mediated by the transcriptional regulation of the color patterning gene, h (Drosophila pannier ortholog). Intraspecific comparative ATAC-seq analysis of the pupal wings revealed that, at the h locus, not the absolute number of Dsx-binding motifs but the proportion of open chromatin regions containing Dsx-binding motifs relative to those lacking such motifs was reduced in strains that had lost sexual dimorphism and acquired novel color patterns, implying that sexual dimorphism evolves based on the balance between novel CREs and Dsx-binding motif density. The present study provides a fundamental molecular framework for understanding how a secondary sexual trait evolves within H. axyridis.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Two mutations in the same MYC-bHLH transcription factor cause segregation of purple coloration of stolons and seed heads in Zoysia japonica x Zoysia matrella F2 and F1 populations</title>
  <dc:creator>Pradhan, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zhao, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Spiekerman, J. J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bennetzen, E.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Khanal, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yu, X.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Milla-Lewis, S.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Conner, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Schwartz, B.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Devos, K. M.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Anthocyanins play diverse roles in plants, including attracting pollinators and protecting cells from oxidative damage. In zoysiagrass, a warm season turfgrass, their accumulation in seed heads and stolons can decrease the aesthetic appeal. In this study, a high-density genetic map with ~8000 single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers organized into 20 linkage groups was generated in a Zoysia japonica acc. Meyer x Zoysia matrella acc. PI 231146 F2 population. Using this genetic map, a large-effect quantitative trait locus (QTL) for anthocyanin variation in stolons and seed heads was mapped to chromosome 12 (PP locus). Variant analysis of a candidate gene for PP, Zjn_sc00004.1.g07010.1.sm.mk, which encodes a MYC-bHLH transcription factor that regulates anthocyanin biosynthesis, revealed a SNP at an exon-intron boundary in Meyer that led to intron retention. Interestingly, an F1 population derived from the same parents segregated for seed head color but uniformly displayed purple stolons. Seed head color in the F1 population co-mapped with the PP locus which, combined with genotypic and yeast two-hybrid analyses, revealed that a SNP in PI 231146 leading to an Ala163Ser substitution in the MYB-interacting N-terminal domain of the same MYC-bHLH transcription factor was likely causal. The Ala163Ser substitution affected interaction of MYC-bHLH with MYB in a MYB-dependent manner. The identified mutations can be exploited to develop cultivars with green seed heads and stolons. The high-marker-density interspecific Z. japonica x Z. matrella F2 genetic map also provides a robust tool for identifying genomic regions and genes of agronomic interest that differentiate the two species.</description>
  <category>genetics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Colour and shape evolution reflect ecological specialisation in Pomacentridae</title>
  <dc:creator>Jimenez, A. G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Salamin, N.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gaboriau, T.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>How ecological pressures shape phenotypic traits such as colouration and morphology is a fundamental question in evolutionary biology. Colouration often mediates functions such as communication, camouflage, and species recognition, while morphological traits influence locomotion, feeding, and habitat use. In reef fishes, both traits exhibit striking diversity, frequently shaped by ecological interactions. The damselfish family (Pomacentridae) exemplifies this variation, displaying a wide range of colouration, morphology, and ecological strategies, including dietary specialisation, mutualistic behaviours, and freshwater tolerance. In this study, we examined 342 Pomacentridae species using an integrative framework that combined colouration and morphometric analyses, ancestral state reconstructions of habitat, diet, and symbiosis, and Phylogenetic Comparative Methods (PCMs). Our goal was to assess how ecological factors have influenced the evolution of phenotypic traits and to identify patterns of convergence linked to ecological specialisation. We found repeated convergent evolution in both colouration and body shape, often associated with similar ecological pressures. Species with specialised diets exhibited consistent morphological adaptations, underscoring the role of trophic ecology in shaping body form. Additionally, we observed a strong association between habitat type and dominant colouration patterns, consistent with a camouflage function. These findings clarify the evolutionary processes driving phenotypic diversity in damselfishes and highlight the importance of ecological adaptation in shaping both morphology and colouration. Our work contributes to a broader understanding of how form and function evolve in response to ecological pressures in coral reef ecosystems.</description>
  <category>evolutionary biology</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Retinal pigment epithelium-derived PD-L1 reprograms microglial cells and protects against retinal degeneration in mouse models of experimental AMD and genetic retinitis pigmentosa</title>
  <dc:creator>Su, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wang, J.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lai, Q.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wang, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liu, P.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tang, Z.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yu, H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Chen, Y.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ma, X.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>HOU, L.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>Retinal degeneration is a leading cause of blindness and a significant health burden during aging worldwide. Because of its complex pathogenic mechanisms, however, effective interventions applicable to multiple retinal degenerations remain limited. Excessive microglia-mediated inflammation is a common pathological feature of different retinal degenerative diseases, and inhibiting these overactive inflammatory responses by reprogramming microglia may provide a therapeutic strategy with broad-spectrum potential. Here, we uncover a novel retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) homeostatic signal, PD-L1, that drives the reprogramming of activated microglial toward a retinal-protective phenotype. Using multiple analyses, including gene expression profiling bioinformatics, adeno-associated virus-mediated RPE-specific gene overexpression, pharmacological, and genetic manipulations, we show that RPE cells upregulate the expression of PD-L1 to modulate microglia for protection against retinal degeneration in an experimental dry AMD mouse model. Bioinformatics enrichment analysis of the high-expression gene signatures of subretinal microglia in AMD patients, combined with pharmacological blocking of NF-{kappa}B activity or using Nlrp3 knockout mice, show that PD-L1/PD-1 signaling suppresses NF-{kappa}B activation in microglia, thereby inhibiting NLRP3 inflammasome priming and attenuating microglia-mediated excessive inflammation. Furthermore, the overexpression of PD-L1 by the AAV8 virus exerts similar microglial reprogramming and retinal protective effects to alleviate retinal degeneration in a preclinical model of retinitis pigmentosa. These findings reveal that RPE-derived PD-L1 suppresses inflammatory reprogramming of subretinal microglia and mitigates retinal degeneration, highlighting a promising proof of concept for PD-L1 as a potential therapeutic target for the broad treatment of retinal degenerative diseases.</description>
  <category>genetics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A comparative GWAS of eye colour in light and dark eye genetic backgrounds defined by HERC2 rs12913832 polymorphism</title>
  <dc:creator>Abbatangelo, C.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lona Durazo, F.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Edwards, M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Parra, E. J.</dc:creator>
  <link>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</link>
  <description>rs12913832, a polymorphism located in an enhancer within the HERC2 gene, which is known to regulate OCA2 transcription, is heavily relied upon as a predictor of light versus dark eyes. Individuals with the GG genotype are projected to have blue eyes, while individuals with the AA or AG genotypes are projected to have darker eye colours (primarily brown). However, eye colour is a polygenic trait, and previous studies have revealed that a significant proportion of individuals self-report an eye colour that is not concordant with their genotype at rs12913832. Herein, we address the question: What common markers are influencing eye colour in individuals whose self-reported phenotype does not correspond to the expected phenotype based on their rs12913832 genotype. Building upon our prior investigation of iris pigmentation genetics in individuals with an expected &quot;blue eye&quot; background (rs12913832:GG genotype) in a sample of the Canadian Partnership for Tomorrows Health (CanPath) cohort, this study extends the analysis to include individuals with an expected &quot;brown eye&quot; background (rs12913832:AA+AG). We identified variants in SLC45A2, TYRP1, TYR, SLC24A4 and TSPAN10, which may influence eye colour presentation in individuals with the rs12913832:GG genotype and variants in IRF4, TYRP1 and OCA2, which may influence eye colour presentation in individuals with the rs12913832:AA+AG genotype. These markers include well-known pigmentation-associated single nucleotide polymorphisms, such as rs16891982 (SLC45A2), rs1126809 (TYR), rs12203592 (IRF4), rs1800407 (OCA2) and rs6420484 (TSPAN10). Several of these loci were replicated using independent quantitative eye colour measures, including heterochromia and CIELAB colour dimensions. This research highlights the importance of gene-gene interactions and the polygenic nature of pigmentation traits, emphasizing modifying effects that can sometimes counteract the dominant influence of rs12913832, contributing to advancements in pigmentation genetics and forensic applications.</description>
  <category>genetics</category>
  <category>new results</category>
  <guid>https://colrverse.github.io/colsci-bot/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
